The following content is provided under a Creative Commons license
Your support will help MIT Open courseware continue to offer high quality educational resources for free
To make a donation or to view additional materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT Open Courseware at ocw.mit.edu
So today what we're going to be doing is
Last week, you gave us some feedback
What you wanted to do in the class
We're gonna go through that and talk about the readings
I'm going to do a little calling on you
and helping you take the class through the readings
and then the 6 or 7 things I'm going to do： history of money
ledgers
fiat currency
central banks and credit cards
and the role of money
Some early digital money
You had the Clark reading as to a bunch of failed attempts
Just all the way through a little bit of mobile money
All the way up to Starbucks and ali pay and yet the riddle remains
We're going to get really deep into Bitcoin in the next three classes
But this is to give some foundational bits of money and ledgers and central banking and technology
And then of course
I always like to finish the class talking a little bit about why we're doing what we're doing between now and then
even though the readings are required
I know you're all busy
I know that you've all got a bunch of classes and
like good business students and business people, you optimize
So I'm trying to give you a sense of why you might read it
Rather than it's required at the end of each class
and how it fits into the coarse narrative
And then we'll do a little bit of conclusions
So the survey results
What did you want to learn
This is really your class
And I'm going to learn as much from you
But hopefully we're going to cover what you want
So here's a list of those things who are at least written by two of you
First was technical things
18 of you said understanding blockchain technology
Hopefully we get to that
But you might find that you'll want to do more after this class
The ecosystem and being able to have an educated discussion
sort of the dinner party conversation around blockchain
I think will be successful
But at the end of the semester
we're going to pull these slides up again
and we'll see how we did as a group
You all talked a lot about applications
How can you actually apply it
Learning it in the venture space
and thinking about where it really works in the world
And I think we're going to spend a lot of time on that in the second half
But all throughout
we're going to be talking about the economics
And what's the reality versus the hype
You also wanted to understand its impact
on people's lives
The regulation
About 6 of you said something about regulation
I'm glad because we're only doing one lecture on that
but we're going to spread it out because as we talked about in our first class
and I'm honored Larry's here again
But we're going to always be thinking about Larry's four ways
And I see -- is it Jihee?
Where are Larry Lessig's
Yeah, you shook your head
Yes, so
I know
It is code and architecture, market, law, and norms
You got it
Does anybody want to say how that relates to blockchain
Why we're chatting about that
Oh my God
I'm going to have to cold call fast, right
You are from R3
Joe? -- Yeah
No, I remember we saw it last class
but I can't relate it now to blockchain
Can you relate to anything in life
Maybe not.  Alan
Help your your table made out
I'm waiting for my moment to shine
This isn't it? -- This isn't it
I'm having fun you know
this is what I'm going to do
I'm just gonna have
it's don't worry about it. Ha
so why do markets, code, law
Did, did I hear
Did I? I can't see your name
but is it Dar?
Yeah
why
Why is that relate to all this
Can you repeat the question?
Jihee
you're going to repeat the question cause you went through it
So how does Larry's four forces relate to
our topic of blockchains
And the four forces, again, are market
So business, law, code or architecture
Call it technology and social norms
So I think it's because it brings like a new way
of doing those things like a new tool in order to-- so
what I got from the reading is like, these ledgers already existed
but given that now we have, like big data
for example,  then like more things going on helps our society
roll it out better.
Good way to say
look it's unfair of me
It wasn't one of the readings
I'm just saying in everything in life
I find these things grind up against each other
I spent a lot of time in Washington in politics
But the markets and how the commercial enterprise
and the economy grinds up against technology
and sort of grinds up against the law
And then of course
just social normative behavior
These four forces in almost everything one does in life
you will find
And so I just ask you to always
whether it's one reading or another reading
bring that to your thought process of this class
I'm not going to assign Larry's assignment
I didn't know he was even going to be here
But I've always thought these, it's a good discipline to think
Okay what are the commercial realities
The markets
What's the technology
Even if it's in an earlier day
and it's a technology of the car replacing the horse and carriage
How does government or the official sector
put it into a set of standards that are required
And then how do we as society
even if it's not required just to have our behaviors
those are the four forces
So that's why
and I probably just failed Larry's class
But that's how I thought about it
I did probably right
And now he's
he's shaking his head
But regulation is just one of those four forces
And that's why I pause there
And so we'll have it in every class
But only one lecture
Money and markets
That's one of the other forces
Five of you said you want to make money
And I applaud those who said that because, why won't they?
You're in a business school
Why not
But investing in trends
Now, there was a bunch of other miscellaneous topics
I'm not going to go through them
I kind of thought the last two were interesting
anecdotes from my past
I'm not sure who said that
I'm not sure what you want to know about, my three daughters
my running or this you know
Wall Street stuff and finance
And I'd like to understand hyperbitcoinization as well
But I don't know who asks that question
I don't know what it is
So I'll try to figure out what hyper...
does anyone want to own up to that question? They were anonymous
All right
So today's study questions
What's the role of money historically
and in today's digital economy
And this is what I'm going to look for discussion
So is anybody who want to tell me what the role of money
what would be your answer to this? Anton?
Umm.. The
The medium of the transaction and enn
and the unit of... like a counting unit
And also, like the state of the value.
So the three classic rolls of money that people talk about.
Kelly, you want to repeat what he just said
That was quite a question, but I think historically
it was pay off debts, starting, you know
and conquering various lands awards
and then also funding trade wars, cutting taxes
So a lot of societal things that drove civilization forward
And what we'll discuss today and
what it is is that money is a social construct
It's something that societies came together
whether it's hard to tell whether it was 5000 years ago
or 8,000 or 10,000 years ago, that it's really
it's a social consensus mechanism
But we're going to chat about the readings in a minute
and come back to that question
What is fiat currency
Is anybody wanna... Tom
You want to tell us what fiat currency is
Umm
It's a shame, tom
See I recognize you
So it's... -- My website
So this is like a established currency
by a central publishing item and a market
Right, so you said it's a central currency and it's by government
Anybody else want to add some things
Is it Kyle?
I would just add that it's not backed by any physical commodity
So it's not backed by any physical commodity
Yeah. Really just the good faith
and credit of the nation that issues it
Daniel, did you want to add anything
I just want to say somewhere that it's not gold backed or anything like that.
But was it always that way
It wasn't originally that way
A fiat currency might be backed by something physical
Was there other
Remind me your name
I'm sorry...  -- Josh  -- Josh
I mean specifically
we used to settle debts
And specifically those to the government
So taxes
All right so for me is for taxes
And remind me your name
Cause I can't see a card
What ? --Sean --Sean
So basically, there's no inherent value in fiat currency
So, so basically, there's no one recognize
that specific currency itself. There's no government
So here is a question for the class
Is there inherent value to non fiat currencies
Because Sean saying that maybe a distinguishing
characteristic of fiat is it has no inherent value
Terry -- Terry
Well actually
the same applies to any commodity that's used to as..., the back
currency in general
because it's just the scarcity of some specific resource and the social
common agreement that that's going to be the  parameter
So, how many people or more in line with Eric
Or there's not one
right answer to this
This is this is a question that's been debated for decades or centuries
But, how many are more on Shawn's camp that...
Well I think it depends that for example
gold is definitely like a social construct
We decide that as a human society
the goal is going to be something valuable
But like if it's like
you know
grains that humans can eat
And you know that I think have the inherent values
So I think there are non-hierarchical currencies that does have inherent values
And that does not have inherent values
Anybody
And what's your... Jihee, yeah
Tom
Tomas？-- Tomas
I just want to say that
the characters there is another component
which, the fact that it is a legal thing for development
in some, in some counties
forced the society to use the
the currency which makes
more comfortable for people to use as a...
Also Tomas is saying that fiat currency is legal tender
So first we have to discuss what is legal tender
is anybody want to knock that one out of the ballpark
who hasn't raised their hand yet now
All right
Well I think that's maybe my earlier comment
It can be used to settle debts and enn...
and specifically
specifically those to the government
So you can use gold as a money
It can be a store of value
It can be a means of exchange
but you can't pay your taxes in gold right
Or is that correct
So 19th century
could you pay your taxes in gold in the US and in Britain
in other countries that had gold currency
Is it just a yes or no
But James
It's yes, but up to 1970s
the gold the currency
the paper currency is attached to the gold standard
So inherently
there is an exchange of value that is pegged by the government or bank or the central bank
So it's almost one of the same thing at the at that time until more recent years
James is saying you could use gold as legal tender
legal tender, again
is something that a society comes together and creates a law
You know back to the Lessig four
that's a... you know society together
It says it's not just a social normative behavior
it's a law
One must accept this in the US and the UK In many countries
it says for all debts
public and private
So a debt to the government or a debt in a store
We're going to get to later as to when is it true that somebody has to take your cash
But I'm going to hold off on that in a minute
And talk about it
But I think also Jihee
said it was somewhere between Sean and Eric
Both physically in the class
And in terms of her articulation that
fiat currency might not have anything inherently behind it
And but gold mostly doesn't have anything inherently behind it
And then some forms of currency like grain
had more
So maybe it's a continuum
Maybe it's not, you know
black and white
100% or 0%
And then we're going to talk a little bit about how Bitcoin fits into it
And our next three classes are going to be really into the technology of Bitcoin
but just just a little bit of teasing out before I go through some lecture slides
Who wants to talk about how Bitcoin might fit into this history of money
And then I'm going to return to that question in about 45 minutes and ask you again
But does anybody want to say from the readings and if you remind me your name
Isabelle -- Isabel.
So with Bitcoin is kind of the same where the value is given by society
except with Bitcoin
it's not backed by any kind of central bank
So people don't think that there is an inherent value
but it like
but the readings pointed out that
they're sort of that same history, except it doesn't have...
So Isabel was saying that Bitcoin fits
into the history of money because
like fiat currencies and like Jihee said about gold
it doesn't necessarily have any inherent monetary value
but it's a societal set of norms that people are accepting it as having value
But the key distinction that Isabel said was that it's no central
It's not backed by any kind of central bank
It's not backed by a central bank or a central authority
Alan?
Yes, so bitcoin,  in my opinion, is unique
because I think the value of bitcoin changes over time
not the fluctuation that we see like $6000 or $19000
but in terms of the power for the utility of the point itself
And, so today, for example
we might be able to buy pizza
or coffee or whatever with Bitcoin
So there is an inherent value in terms of minimum exchange
And it will change as society adopts it more and more
So I think it's hard to define if there is an inherent folly or not
So Alan is raising that Bitcoin
If I can put some words in your mouth
and tell me if I'm correct
that Bitcoin might have some distinguishing features
from even fiat currency that its value is shifting over time with adoption
And is that, I mean
you didn't use that word
Please let me know your name again
Brotish
right, like British
but with an o
you told me earlier
Brotish
So I think
Another way is thinking of the thing that is is the evolution of the ledger technology
like accounting and the evolution of money along with it
So initially that we saw in the reading the
how it happened in the previous four occasions
And at the end of the three layers and then distributed layer
which is kind of the fundamental, four of the fundamental blocks of bitcoin -- Right
so that is another way of kind of a natural progression of how money evolved
So, Brotish?
Yeah
So what brotish is raised is also Bitcoin fits into the history of ledgers
whether it's double entry ledgers as recognized through tea accounts
or other forms of ledgers that it adds to this whole long history of ledgers
I agree with that
And it's a new form of keeping ledgers, Elan
So Bitcoin is also similar to gold
There is an element of scarcity
Of scarcity
Yeah
So we cannot generate that many Bitcoin -- Correct
and only generate Bitcoin every 10 minutes
keeps happening every four years
So scarcity
it seems like scarcity and ledgers are important components of ... Viva
So it does have a fixed demand
Like, umm sorry, a fixed supply
like you said
in terms of scarcity
but the more we adopt it
the more it becomes divisible in terms of units
And so we can increase its use
Because now you can divide, you know
you can divide them up to
This is good. So divisibility is another characteristic of money
Scarcity
Adoption as Alan said
Ledgers
Sorry, Tomas
We mention decentralization
because this implementation
make feasible the Bitcoin and makes feasible
to implement this kind of thing in the decentralized environment
So without any central power to do
define or dictate the supply and other aspects of the concept
I will take one more
and then I'll start to talk about history
Why don't we go here to remind me your name
Alexis -- Alexis
...money and like other forms of currency
Even if it's not controlled by like central government or central bank
like there is no fixed exchange rate fluctuate extremely quickly
We have other type of appearances
So I mean
it's still very different
So, Alexis
if I understand Alexis's point is that there is no fixed exchange rate
About Bitcoin we're talking about
but couldn't we really broaden that to all forms of currency
I mean
what really is the exchange rate between an ounce of gold and a bushel of corn
Yes and no
I mean yes
but like for example
like some state do control
stainless steel with other tenants
Alright good point
So Alexis is saying yes and no
because some governments try to fix
Now back to markets
How well has that worked when governments try to fix an exchange rate
I mean just a sense of the class
Does that work well
so it sort of might work well in temporal short periods
works less well for you know decades on end
I'll take one more, and then I'm just
I want to go through a couple...
Just one comment. That way you can teach hours of work
That's how economies define it previously, right
But I just want to ask
what is a ledger?
What is a ledger
Very good question
I'm gonna be chatting of it that in a minute
But does anybody wanna
hit that
I'm sorry
No, over here
...It's just a numerical record of everything recorded, in a fashion
So it's... -- A numerical record
I think that's a good thing
A ledger is basically a way to record
Economic activity or social relationships or financial relationships
I would say it's both a way to record economic activity
And it's a system of recording financial relationships
And while I didn't assign these readings
some very good academic research suggests that the first
methods of writing and symbols of writing had to do with
numbers and had to do with ledgers rather than words and communication
Because it's so fundamental to society to record
various economic transactions or to record the financial relationships amongst
between members of a community
whether it was a small village or when society burst out of villages
thousands of years ago. Is that help?
We'll be back to it
and better that you ask that here than in your accounting fundamentals class
I don't know
So the readings we've sort of talked about the readings
have any of you actually watched the little 3 minute video
did you
what do you think? Just, I mean, just as a...
I'm sorry, here, we haven't chatted yet
I think the blog based principle was
that any currency or anything for that matter
has value equivalent to what the socity assigns to it
Right
Because the video basically just showed the guy
who created his own galaxy and was just selling into the public
And his whole claim was that it is real if you believe it is real
Right,  so it was just
it was a nice little ditty, in a way
Matthew, I'm sorry?
I would have given him $1 for it
You would have given him $1? Great
Seeing how much the pizzas went for
You know... -- Who knows
Would anybody else have given him a dollar for it
No, maybe
Oh, oh. But you would have
Yeah
I actually
I am working with local currencies
It is kind of the same
but they are just
you can use it just locally
And I mean, it keeps the money inside the community
that decides to use that way of transaction
We're going to refer back to each of these ratings as we go through the next 45 minutes
But yeah
I was wondering if he was actually breaking the law
by launching his own competing currency for the US dollar?
Is that a legitimate-- Obviously, it didn't compete with the US dollar
but... -- You know
you raised a very good question
I'm not aware of any statute federal or state
that says there's an absolute monopoly
or in forms of currency as there is and other things
like you know
that slot in the door
that's called the where you can put a letter through the door or a mailbox
There's actually a law that says that the US Postal Service has a monopoly
And that's why UPS
is not allowed to put their boxes or anything in there
There is a government fiat monopoly
but you raise a very good question
what we've found in the last 10 years with Bitcoin
without with really oversimplifying is
that it is legal to create your own form of money
as Bitcoin is possibly this money
But you have to comply with all the other laws
and all those other laws that we'll talk about in other lectures in essence
fall into buckets of guarding against illicit activity
So the bank secrecy act and all the laws related to any money laundering and terrorism
finance and so forth
That one still has to pay your taxes
if you're gaining or losing on this investment
that the Federal Reserve and other authorities around the globe still
want to ensure for financial stability
the fellow on the streets of
I don't remember what city New York selling his dollars when Matthew bought it for a dollar
And I think over here, Brianna?
What's that -- My name?
Yes
Priscilla, bought it
It's probably we're going to have the society is still going to be stable
It's gonna be alright
But if millions of people were buying it then people might worry
And then there's the third big bucket that
we look at as investor and consumer protection
But I think it's allowed
So we'll refer to these, Joaquin
and then I'm gonna go on
Can you legally pay
for example, salaries
in bitcoin in the US ?
Yes, and why is it that you can legally pay for wages in Bitcoin in the US
So anybody
I know it's outside of the readings
but why do you think it is allowed in this society
Is it, Kyle
Wouldn't those compensation phones be allowed under a new contract
So, most things you could pay somebody in these placards
I doubt really that you're going to value of that much
but you could pay somebody in this
You could pay somebody in gold, euros, bitcoin
And there are firms that are pegged
Usually they are developing blockchain applications
And interestingly
they have to compute the value of the wages
to do withholding taxes
because the US government will not accept taxes in Bitcoin
So they figure out the fair market value
And there are companies in the US that pay people in Bitcoin
who are doing development work around blockchain applications
But the taxes need to be computed and analyzed and then paid in US dollars because
and there was a legislative initiative in Arizona
earlier this year where a state legislature wanted to
have Arizona be the first state in the land to accept Bitcoin for taxes
but it failed in committee
It didn't even get a full vote of it
I can't remember
It was the Arizona Senate or the Arizona House of Delegates
but, so just a little walk through the history
I was going to do a little history of money and have some fun
So in Ethiopia
people put together salt bars
This is not that long ago
Salt, as Jihei have said earlier
is really valuable in society
And they standardize the shape and size and said
here is salt bars
We're going to get to a little bit later
All the characteristics of money
But what else do you think
A salt bar in Ethiopia
as opposed to maybe some other country
What did it have as well as to why people might use that
Oil -- What's that?
Crude oil -- Crude oil, all right
I hadn't thought of that
I'm going to keep thinking about that
It's not a, it's not a common characteristic of money
But why salt bars? what else might it have in Ethiopia
Are you gonna say that
You can use salt to preserve or... -- You can preserve food
But because it was mined
there was some scarcity as well as and a lot of currencies
a lot of moneys over time have that fundamental issue
Cowie shells from West Africa
Does anyone know the history of when Cowie shells
got really debased and stopped being used from the readings
I can't remember that was in the readings or not
They got debased when Europeans started to realize that they were accepted as a value
And it was a very sad and terrible history too
because it's related to the whole slave trade
but that the Europeans could figure out that societies accepted
This is something of value
But they also debase that currency
and they debase the land and capture people as slaves
I mean, it was a quite a collection of not particularly good things going on
Talley sticks in England
So anybody from the readings
because there was a little bit of the debate
in the first reading about the history of money
and wanna chat and I'll pull up the rye stones for me
how this fits into that first reading and the debate between
has the money come from a history of border
Or did money come from a history of ledgers and credit
which is kind of a setup of that first
I think the first reading
Any thoughts
Which ones are these
These four bits of money
Early money or more about maybe border
So there are two... two theory, right
That which corresponds to this one
And it was a way to measure that
Which one?
The sticks -- The sticks
The tally sticks, yes,  correct
Which is the second one on here that has to do with debts actually
And credits -- The stones
The stone, the Rai stones
So it's remarkable
The Rai stones were so that on this island of Yap
they couldn't possibly lug it around and use it
You know, in traditional medium of exchange
but it was viewed as, well
I have 1/6 of this bride's stone
You have 1/16
And then if I make an exchange
we'd remember
And the society was small enough to keep a form of ledgers
even to the extent that when a Rai stone was lost in a river
they said, you know, the river Rai stone
we each have this piece
So on the island of Yap
I can assure you these stones could not be used for anything else
Does anyone know
Because it was outside the readings
What made these stones so scarce
So Rai stones required on an island about 200 km away from the app
So were they exceedingly hard to get, like gold
Like mining of gold
What else's mind these days
That might be a money
Lithium
What's that?
Can I hear everybody
I'm saying lithium
What's that
The batteries... for batteries, is gonna be
very difficult in the future for electric batteries and whatnot
And what is mind right now
That's at the center of this class
Bitcoin -- Bitcoin, right
The Yap stone was, in essence,  quarried
a couple of hundred kilometers away
And what debased that currency was when sailors from England came
there's a specific sailor
I think his name was O'keefe in the late 19th century
And he realized that these stones were valuable
And he went to the other island
and he started quarrying and came back and forth
And within a few years
the whole economic system collapsed
We moved to metal money
At first
it wasn't really stamped
It was just heavy
It was hard to quarry bronze in Rome
There's some China's in Sweden
These were starting to be stamped by the official sector
And then we had minted money
starting somewhere around 2500 years ago
And there's debates as to whether it started in Greece or in China
And but
but where an official emblem was placed upon a scarce resource that was used
Paper money came along in a sense
for what reason?
Why, why did
why did society first tip into paper money
Cause there's not enough gold to back it up
I mean, like because there's
One reason
Not enough gold
I'm sorry, I haven't
I think it's just easy to... -- Easy to use
It's kind of heavy
especially if there wasn't gold
And if it was copper bronze
it was just heavy
Or if it was wheat
you have to put it in a storage unit
So the first paper money's from China were basically warehouse receipts
And I spent five years running something called commodity Futures trading Commission
And so I guess I learned a lot about warehouse receipts, commodity receipts
where you put a commodity in a warehouse
And then you got a piece of paper that said
yes, you have that commodity there
So the first paper moneys were basically warehouse receipts in China
because whatever it was, grain or gold
And then you had a piece of paper backing it
These are £5 notes from England and the continental notes in the US
But between so that that note in China is about 700 years old
But before between that first paper money and the 18th century
Who do you think we're kind of the first bankers in the 7th
late 17th century, early 18th century
Who were, what craft had they been in before they were in banking
--Trading...  --Alpha --International trading
International trade
They actually did something more local
I talked... just talked about this
like the ones that have lands and all the...
the ones that have lands and all the...
Lanes? -- Lands...
Land. Land. No, they had something else that they were doing
Tom? -- Printmakers --They were printmakers
I like that
We're not there yet
Money lenders?
What's that?
They're underwriting insurance
A little bit later
They were doing agriculture?
It's definitely outside of the reading
They're goldsmiths
The... Some of the first dominant bankers in London
They were small goldsmiths and they took the gold
They gave you a piece of paper
And then they went from there
And then all of a sudden
they figured out how to do credit
Later in the semester
we're going to talk about Bitcoin credit
It's not there yet, by the way
I think in the next 18 to 36 months
we're going to start seeing crypto lending and crypto finance in the form
similar to what the goldsmiths were doing in the early 17 hundreds in England
Nolan
Is that scalable with the finite number of frequent
in your opinion
So very good question
Is it scalable to land against a finite currency
I think so
but it's not
it's not done yet
right
Yeah
because when you
when you run money to someone
I guess it couldn't be in the form of a Bitcoin
but you can lend someone dollars
they could redeem in bitcoin
You'd be increasing kind of the
money supply
So you don't need
you're not moving money around directions
So this is exactly the central of commercial banking today
It's called fractional banking, we will be talking about that in a bit
But is to.... yes, you could
you could land and then have a multiplier effect
You also had that banks come up and started to issue private bank notes
private bank notes
Effectively a liability of that bank
and saying it would trade
and the history of private bank notes is usually what
you know, good until it's really bad
And the history of money
a lot of private banks
went bust in this country around the revolutionary period again around the civil war
And in essence
that's what we have now with 1600 different cryptocurrencies
we have a sort of a new period of a little bit of private property currencies
And I only ask you to remember that as we start to look at Icos
initial coin offerings and so forth
So ledgers, the earlier question is
what was a Ledger? Chermo
You asked it can you remember what's a ledger
It's a way to record economic transaction
Yeah, principal recordings of accounts and 5000 years ago
you had a little reading on this
Just a medium post It wasn't meant to be a deep back economic academic paper
but it was to try to get
get the class thinking about
ledgers
This is the personal ledger of George Washington
our first president
He was 15 years old when he kept this ledger
and he apparently kept ledgers until his death
And let's see
52 years later
But so ledgers could be kept just to record the transactions of the day
He's got one up there
Mary Washington
it must have been a cousin
Or I can't remember if it was his mother was
so if they're the principal recordings of accounts and I've already sort of said this
they record economic activity and financial relationships
economic activity in a sense of transactions
financial relationships
What's the key financial relationship
And a ledger might record on
I'm sorry
Debt
Kelly said it, debt, and it goes back to the debate you had in the reading is money history of border
Did it come out of border
Did it come out of a sense of debts and credit and store of value for this purpose
Today, It doesn't really matter
It may have come from both
but know that it has both sides and ledgers have both sides too
and when we're talking about Bitcoin
Bitcoin, you will see is a
is a mechanism to store transactions
Some other blockchains
like Ethereum stores balances
So even in the blockchain world
you will see some that are balanced ledgers
and some which are transaction ledgers
not to lose you and confuse you
It's an important part of of what is blockchain technology
Some types of ledgers
I just mentioned one transactions versus balance
George Washington's ledger
by the way
I think, was a transaction ledger
He was just keeping, you know
a list of sales and movements
But I haven't studied President George Washington's ledger close enough
Does anybody know enough accounting
to tell me the difference between a general ledger and a subledger
or a general ledger and a supporting ledger
I mean, I don't want to do the whole lecture myself
How many of you have taken accounting
I taught undergraduate accounting ones
Sorry
So those of you who just put up your hand
who took accounting
did I see in the back of the room
Did you take accounting
And that's Aviva
I'm an accountant, actually
all right, all right
Did you pass the CPA
Oh we have a Certified Public Accountant who's
going to tell us the difference between a general ledger and a sub ledger
General Ledger is one that that records all kinds of transactions
any kind of activity that takes place to record in the general ledger and sub ledgers
You can call them as like a specialization
So let's say if there's a salary or to be paid
there will be a salary subledger
But it will also go in the general legend
and the other part of the transactions in the salary legend, or if there's capital
Or if there is some new stuff that you buy
So all of that goes specifically in the general legend
Each of them have their own specific letters
If you wanna say how much you spend on
salaries for the month and you go to your salary legacy
But if you wanna see over how much money you spend and how much is moved around
then you look at your general ledger
Aviva clearly said it better than I could have
Thank you
Now we know we have one CPA in the class
But the importance
it's not just a passing note
the importance of a general ledger and sub ledgers is there's a hierarchy as well
Subledgers have more detail
and maybe the net numbers kept on the general ledger
that is at the heart of our system of banking
and is at the heart of our system of financial markets
where the central bank is like a general ledger for money
and every commercial bank, all 9,000 of them or so in the US
in essence keep a sub ledger for money
But they do not have control of what I will call the master ledger
or general Ledger at the Federal Reserve
Then a third distinction about ledgers
A single entry a little
young, 15 year old George Washington was keeping a single entry ledger
just a list of things that were going on
And I didn't think I was going to bore the class with readings
about double entry bookkeeping because you've taken accounting
But does anybody want to tell me other than Aviva
What double entry bookkeeping
And she'll bail you out...
Double-entry bookkeeping basically means that any transaction has two places in the letter
One on the credit side and one on the standard side
because every transaction was one person lending
whereas the other person is getting... the thing
Yeah, it works for me
Anybody else wanted a different view
In other words,  ...asset and liability... two sites and then... to balance each other...
There's a balancing between assets and liabilities
And then the resulting bit of capitalism in it
Is if assets are more than liabilities
the rest is capitol
So at the heart of capitalism
in a sense
is double entry bookkeeping
And in fact
while it probably goes back a little over 1000 years
when it was truly written up by the Italians in the 13 hundreds
it start started to help
You are come out of the dark ages
I mean, the commercial renaissance of the middle ages
Some would say was in part not entirely
but in part, on the backs of double entry bookkeeping
So ledgers matter is my point
They're not going to be the heart and soul of this class
But Bitcoin
which is a transaction ledger
Ethereum
which is a balance ledger
our financial system
which is all set up on ledgers
is a relevant sort of subtext
You don't have to be afraid of it just as you don't have to be afraid of
of hashing power that we'll be talking about on Thursday and cryptography
But you'd have to have some you know
sort of basic sense of where's
where's Bitcoin fitted in terms of ledgers
does anybody, I didn't fill this slide in
You'll find out it's blank
Does anybody want to tell me what some characteristics of a good ledger
Because again
as you start to think about your blockchain projects later in the semester
it's like what makes a good ledger that I don't have any answers here
The bitcoin were immutable
So you want it to be immutable, maybe
Thalita, can you do me a favor and keep these
We'll put them on the slides, when we put
we'll keep the classes list and we'll put them in the slides, immutable
I like that
that anybody else want to grab something
which is a good ledger
Time stamped
What is that?
All right So that
you know when you made your entry
Kelly
Ownership -- Ownership
What do you mean by ownership
Essentially the receiver and the person giving
So essentially
who's taking what he's giving
So it was a transaction
the two counterparties to the transaction
right
And if it's a balance than who owns the balance
I was just adding a little bit to
Let's see if we have a new name or face back here on the
on the back table
I haven't chatted with you yet
What is that
Ross -- Ross
Thank you
Ross
Good to meet you
Pleasure to meet you, as well. Accuracy
Accuracy
So Ross says accuracy
And could we take one or two more
Just a description of the transaction
So Andrew says a description of the transaction
And last, Mr... -- Comprehensive
What's that? Comprehensive
So all good attributes of a characteristics
somebody's burning desire that we missed one or two?
Jihei? All right
I just was curious on consistency maybe
but I don't know if that's...
Well, I think that's inside of immutability
that in essence
that it's valid that you can't
you can't change it
You can't counterfeit it and the like
And what you'll find is the characteristics of a good ledger
is also in some part similar to the characters of good money
They're not identical
but they overlap a lot
payment systems
I'm just going to say one line about it
It's a method basically
to amend and record changes in a ledger for money
I know it's not what you usually think about a payment system
but if you go into Starbucks
and buy a cup of coffee
and use your cell phone
aren't you really just amending a set of ledgers
Starbucks is
ledger goes up
And yep
your ledger goes down
Well
your monetary ledger goes up
Your utility
your fulfillment from that latte might go up
I'm talking about the financial ledger
So I just wanted to ground when we talk about payment systems to think about
it's really just a way to amend
Usually two parties ledgers
one going up
one going down
Now in an earlier time
it was handing somebody a bit of gold
or a bit of silver
and it was not recorded on central ledgers
But we already live in an age of electronics
So this is really what a payment system largely is
It's not entirely
There's still some other ways to do finance
So what were some early forms of payment systems that did just that
That moved and changed ledgers
They're called negotiable orders
I would dare say that most of you probably have not
used negotiable orders of withdrawal that much
in the last week or the last month
Is anybody here written a personal check in the last week
But in an earlier era
it would have been the whole class
anybody in the class
not even have a checkbook
Three quarters of the class
Larry how's that make you feel -- Getting old
But a checkbook is, in essence
with a... what do you put on a check?
What's... These are... this is all about Bitcoin now
I'm not doing this just as a
walk down memory lane for Larry and myself
What's the... what are the important pieces of a negotiable order
Withdrawal or check
Put your signature on it
So there's a signature
What else is there
I want to get to people I haven't talked to, in the back
I can't remember your name
Me? I'm Dana
You put who you're paying to, how much, and what it's for
All right
so there is a bunch
So a signature
a payee
how much and what it was for
what else
There is an account number and routing numbers
Account numbers and routing numbers
So think about account numbers and routing numbers is to
just say, in essence
what ledger is this coming from
And the payee is the ledger
It's to whom it's going
And I'm sorry, Dan?
Also a date -- And a date
So there's a time stamp
a signature
a payee
the payor in the form of the account number
and an amount
Those five are really critical
and you'll find them are going to be right in the middle of all this Bitcoin
And then the reason why you're
you know
some other information
I'm sorry, was there something else
Kyle -- Kyle -- I just have a question
Would you consider something like PayPal
or Venmo like a negotiable order?
They may be
They may be new forms
They're certainly parts of the payment system
Why they might not be negotiable orders or withdrawal
They might not be a direct authorization for a bank
with one ledger to move money to another ledger
They might be moving it on their own ledger, that's a...
but you're asking the right question
So some early money that we already talked about
that was Ledger
Were the tally sticks in England and the Yap stone
These were ledger types and forms of money
and was kind of interesting
So ledgers didn't just come with electricity and computers
So now let's get back to fiat currency
The heart of a earlier question
And we already talked about it
So let's see how the professor did
Cause you already said some of the things that you said
were fiat currency. One social and economic consensus
I don't... I'm in this school that it's just part of the history
It's not that different than everything that came
even though it built on that promissory note from China 700 years ago
in the private bank notes
it got in the goldsmiths in the 17 hundreds
But ultimately governments took control
That represents central bank liabilities
And that's important
It's a liability of a central bank
It's not an asset
It's their liability side
But it's also
guess what
There's a second form of money
And that's when you make a
you have a deposit in a bank
That's a liability of a commercial bank
Central bank is the top gold standard of sense using the word gold
But it's the top ledger
Commercial banks are like subledgers in a sense
Please, Alan?
Sure. I'm not an economist or anything
but what does it mean to be
for a coin or a note to be a liability of the central bank?
What does that actually mean?
So before I answer
does anybody want to try to answer what it is?
Eric?
Liability is basically an obligation, to, in this case, pay someone an amount
So because it's a social consensus
it's a very good question that Alan asked is
what does it mean to be a liability of a central bank
when it's just the currency in our pocket
This Federal Reserve note
this says Federal Reserve note on it
And
Right
We can pass it around
I'm not afraid it's only a dollar
but, you know, right
You want me to pass around 20s and then I want them back
But it says better reserve note, right?
So it's a liability of the commercial bank
in a earlier day
it was said you could exchange it for gold or silver
Right, so that's what I don't understand...
But by the 1930s for retail deposits in the middle of the depression
President Roosevelt said, no more
You can not
You could not redeem gold and silver
And then President Nixon in the 1970 said in the official sector
that he was going off of the... until that point in time
other governments could redeem in gold
But when paper money started
it was not backed by gold
We had a period of the gold standard we were on and off of it
We fell off of it after World War... during World War I
We went back on it
It would be a false narrative to say that we were on
the gold standard for our first 140 years
I just wanted to clear that up
I mean, we sort of went on the gold standard
We went off
we went back on and so forth
But it is a liability on the books and records
So as a matter of accounting and double entry bookkeeping
I will show you in a minute
The balance sheet of the Federal Reserve
And I'll come back to this question
Is that all right
Can you clarify what is the bank liable for?
So before, it gave me a dollar
and I could go to the dollar and get back to the gold, right?
Right
Now, what is it liable for now
It is, in essence, a social
It's the first point
the... I'm going to separate it
The central bank is liable that they will move on its ledgers
If you want to move that to somewhere else
So you could take that physical $1 in and say
I want to deposit this in a bank
and they have to record it on the ledger of that bank
That is what they're... that is
And the US government
which is technically separate from the central bank
or the UK government or the Chinese government
They are all technically separate from their banks
People's Bank of China or the Bank of England
Their governments are saying they will accept it for payments against taxes
So there's a so... set of social constructs
It relies on a...
I'm going to just go through this to answer your question
It relies on a system of ledgers
and it's an integration of those ledgers between the
banking system and the commercial banks
In the US we have about 9000 commercial banks
And what the Federal Reserve is saying
But it's true about the People's Bank of China
It's true about the European Central Bank
Each of these central banks are basically saying
if you bring your paper money in
we will record it on the ledger of a commercial bank
and you can pay your taxes to our sister over here called the government
That's... I'm sorry to let you down
It's not more than that
Sorry, Alan
I have a potential answer
I might be totally wrong
Please, go
I think it's a legal and sustainable way to conduct a Ponzi scheme
With, yeah, with a proper Ponzi scheme
where the value will increase by 1% to 3%
If you.. if a central bank reaches the goal of inflation
Right, any other points of view in that
I saw
I don't
I don't know your name
Oh
no
you don't want to say anything
No
all right
I think it will go back to point one, right
So it's a construct that someone would give you something
So your dollar where the central bank
the central bank owes you that dollars worth of whatever you desire
and someone will happily take that dollar
from the central bank and give you the goods that you want
So it's a roundabout way of...
it's a way of transacting something
whetever the dollar has...
It's also central bank liability
Because like whenever the government has sovereign debt
it can just issue new notes
It's liable
So that's why it's a liability because you can only issue notes
against a certain amount of reserves that you...
So that's why it...
That's why you repudiate as a liability
because you can't just issue new notes whenever you need them
You can't just make new money out of thin air
So you're liable for every new note
I'm gonna take one more comment on this
and then give a couple more things, here
The currency is actually a small part of the
the total reserves
the federal reserve system
I think maybe the bank reserves
or maybe a more applicable application
because the bank can actually require the Fed to print money by making more loans
So in that way, is that mechanism to ensure that liability
So I'm very pleased with this discussion
Even Alan's contributions about the schemes
This is the debate
If Jay Powell were here
how many of you know who Jay Powell is
Who is Jay Powell
It's a lab  -- Jay powell
No, who's Jay powell
Head of the...
Head of the Federal Reserve
Thank you, sorry
But if Jay Powell were here
he'd have a laugh along with what Alan just said
But, he would say, also
the liability is a social liability as well
that a central banker
to their core beliefs of what they are trying to do
is ensure for the stability of this social thing we call money
and to make sure that it doesn't get debased and it has some value
And so it's accepted for taxes
We talked about notes and coins are legal tender for all debts
Public and private
I walk into a Starbucks and I say I'd like a cup of coffee
Here's my $5 or whatever it costs these days
does the person behind the counter have to brew the coffee
Is just a yes or no?
Can I see?
Who wants to go for it?
There's a no from Christopher
What, Chris? Alright
there's a no from Chris, who agrees with Chris
Okay
they brew the cup of coffee
I go to the other side of the counter
The coffee sitting there, now
Do they have to accept my $5 at that point
Yes
before they brew the coffee
nobody has to take dollars
But once a debt is established
they produced the good
They provided the service
They have to take it
Just a small little thing
That's what legal tender is
So there's many establishments around the globe
that are basically now putting little signs out
We don't take Swedish corona
We don't take this
We don't take that
In paper form
they'll still take it electronically
And there's sort of
there's a new little bit of definition thing going on about legal tender
There's also some unique tax treatments
but I'm not going to go through the currency
So central banking and money
We talked about a little bit
This is a kind of chart that I borrowed from
from a... somebody else's paper
But the central banks at the top is at the center
And if Alice and Bob and we'll be talking about Alice and Bob in Bitcoin time
so you can pull this chart down later
I want to transact
And they're at the same commercial bank, bank number one
then commercial bank number one has to change their ledgers
moving money from Alice to Bob
In essence
if you're both two people at Bank of America
you can move the your balance at Bank of America
But if you're a bank of America going over to Citicorp
then something has to go between two ledgers
Bank of America's Ledger and City Corpse Ledger
And the only way to transact between 2 bank's ledgers
is some balancing act has to happen
at the top ledger called the central bank
And later
when we talk about payment systems
I'm going to use this slide again later in the semester
That's why I'm not going to spend as much time now on it
We're going to talk about ledgers
And when you move money between 2 banks
it's all within one closed system
that countries or that they society's central banking system
But then it gets really a little bit more iffy and woolly
when you are moving from one currency to another currency
Because how do you make two closed ledger systems operable?
Not for today
but we'll go through that later when we do payment systems and the like
The central bank
The US central bank
This was the only good slide I could find
which was about a year old
Its liabilities and assets are about 4 and 1/4 trillion dollars
$4.3 trillion. $1.7 trillion of that is in currency
Do I get my $1 back
By the way I mean
my liability
Yeah
So $1.7 trillion of those greenbacks are in circulation
And remarkably
even though half of you probably don't use cash that much
you don't even have checking accounts
The amount of cash in circulation is growing faster
than the economy in most developed nations
Why do you think that is?
Probably one word
The amount of 2008 crisis...
Oh that's more than one word
Drugs
Trust
Oh trust
I thought you said drugs
Trust
Well it does have to do a trust
but it also has to do with drugs
Paper currency is a wonderful method of of money laundering
drug running and a store of value
So there's certain segments of our economy
and segments of the worldwide economy
that does not want to be in the electronic banking system
I'm going to slip through these quickly
but there's another piece that we need for this whole class
and for the semester is credit and credit intermediation
But just a little thing
Credit cards started only 60 or 70 years ago
But they go back to a book a little over 100 years ago
The word credit cards used 18 times in this book where
a science fiction writer in 1887 said
what would the world be like in the year 2000
And it was the first we used the word credit card
and he said they would
society would have a form of money
And you could have credit against it
And it's a fascinating thing that somebody could be that visionary
But there were merchant cards starting
So maybe he wasn't so visionary
Oil companies in the 1920s
charge cards were starting
but they were single merchant cards
You could have credit from that merchant
In 1946 in a bank in Brooklyn
a guy named Biggins, started with that
That was the first real charge it
You could charge things in a few dozen places in Brooklyn
literally
And then all of a sudden it took off
Diners Club started in the early 1950s
They found that they could get a bunch of restaurants to say
wouldn't you want to extend credit
And we'll back at American Express in the mid 1950s
And then finally in the mid 1960s
Bank America, which is that time was a California bank
figured out they would create a co-operative with a bunch of other US banks to extend credit
And the credit boom took off
And what was interesting
the laws to regulate all this didn't come until the 1970s
at least in the US
the Fair Credit Reporting Act and all the other laws
There's three big ones in the 1970s
So those who... I go to conferences sometime to talk about Bitcoin regulation
and they say, well, why can't the government solve this now
I sort of remind them that it took 15 to 20 years from the introduction of credit cards
kind of in the early to mid 1950s
And the real takeoff in the 1960s
It was 1974 1977
The three big credit laws
So if you're going to be an entrepreneur in Bitcoin
know that it could be 15 years
until there's some crypto loss in the future
that was the processing machine from the 1950s
I know I made it too small
Sorry
Visa made it better
And then of course
that's what we all see today
how your cards get processed
So the role of money we've talked about
So I'm going to skip over that
But now the characteristics of money
what makes a good money, we talked about some of this earlier
it's durable
meaning that, that salt cube wasn't the greatest because of a lot of rain came
That would be kind of wash away
Gold and silver metals are durable
They are portable
The heavier it is
the less portable it is
And that's why gold was a better money than silver
you could move it
And better than copper bronze
It was divisible, easily
You could slice things up
uniform and fungible
And anyone who is down the rabbit hole on this stuff
If you really want to learn about money
read about Crawford versus Royal Bank in 1749
There was a gentleman at the early part of paper money that mailed two £20 notes
And he wrote his name on them
They got lost in the mail
and he took the banks to court
to say those were mine when they were found
And there was no law in Scotland or in England at the time as to what to do about it
But if you lose or somebody stole a piece of art
you get it back
And the law was settled in 1749 that you actually don't get your money back
Does anybody want to guess as to why the courts
It was a matter of first interpretation
the courts had no
they had no jurisprudence on this before 1749
Why did the courts decide
that a piece of art was different than currency
And it goes to the fundamental of what money is, fiat money is
Anybody want to take a guess as to why the courts
They could've gone the other way
How could you tell if someone really owned money?
He signed it
It was actually... the facts were clear
It was the currency he signed
I'm just helping you out so that... that's a good point
But he signed it
It can't be used as a medium of exchange if you
if it doesn't belong to the person...
In essence, if you were to go back and read
there is some history on this, and read the court cases
This was the point
The court basically said we have to make this a medium of exchange
This is a greater social good
It has to be fungible
And the Royal Bank of Scotland was
of course
the kind of
you know
closer to the courts than this gentleman
Crawford
but the banks were also saying that we can't keep track of this
So it was a mixture of the two
but it made it fungible
Eric
Was it those specific notes that he had signed?
Yeah
and in 1749
they all had serial numbers and they were signed in a way that not today
of course
they're acceptable
And they're stable
And we're going to talk a lot about the last point
They're stable because they're hard to mine
And Bitcoin has that embedded in it as well
the design of money is really important as well
You can make it a token
A token is like something physical
or a count based
We are, of course
now living in a world of account based money
and its digital not physical
It can be issued by the private sector just like bank notes in the 18th century
or private sector like Bitcoin or it can be central
It can be widely acceptable or just wholesale
There are forms of wholesale money
One of the biggest forms of wholesale money is the central banks'
Reserves are only available to the commercial banking system
We're going to study this money flower later
but I put it in the slides because, this
I didn't create this flower
You have a reading later in the semester from the Bank of International Settlement
that has this money flower in it
But it's basically across these four things
is a token or account based physical or digital private or central or widely accessible
And then all monies fall into one piece of this money flower
There's a Professor Garrett that came up with this flower
And there is an optional reading later in the semester from him
You had a reading from Clark
There's not enough time
but all this stuff failed
Does anybody want to give me a flavor for one or two reasons
why a bunch of digital cash failed
Did anybody read the clerk reading the history of some DigiCash
Oh, Alan read it
Anybody else read it
Over here
I can't... --Zhan
Don. So what did you
Zhan -- What?
zhan -- zhan, zhan
what did you take from the reading?
Why did these all fail?
What's like the one or two biggest reasons they failed
Most of them still relied on kind of some form of a central authority
All right, they relied on central...
DigiCash certainly did it, David Chaum's case, and some of the others
Any other big reason? Alan, did you have--
There wasn't enough adoption by merchants, I recall
Definitely not adoption by merchants
Very good
Third reason why they failed one
That's at the core of what Bitcoin solved
Incentivizing like a decentralized network to keep that ledger, maintain the ledger
Alright, and standardizing the ledger, behind her
They couldn't solve the double spend Problem
That's it, couldn't spend the double spend problem
Could a currency be spent not just once, but twice
So there's 4 things that were raised
Four things that about centralization
The double spend
They couldn't get merchants to adopt it
And there was a couldn't
Some form of consensus as to what the ledger was
I'm going to flip through these quickly
but digital and mobile money did happen
We were asked about PayPal earlier
It was 1998 in Norway
Eriksen and Telenor had the first mobile app
and it was to get movies on your mobile phone
1999, Alipay comes along that
We'll talk a lot about when we do payments later
And of course
M-pesa so that we talked about a little last week in Kenya
where Safaricom noticed that a bunch of money... near money
It was mobile minutes that was being used as money in Kenya
And now there's 20 million users of that
And of course
there's a bunch of regulations now and so forth
Starbucks started in 2011
And then, of course
it's now off to the races in mobile money
One of the key things about mobile money
we will discuss and learn together is the question
Each one of these is where is the stored value
And I have to tell you
sometimes I get quite confused when I research a new app
Are they storing the value
or are they just a processing provider to move...
As we said earlier
payment systems move and change and amend other ledgers
in a number of these like M-Pesa
Initially they were storing the value
and mobile app Starbucks stores the value
but many of them are just applications
computer code to move the ledger somewhere else
But the riddle remained
You remember that riddle
How to move money
Peer to peer without a central authority
And that's what I'm asking for next class, Thursday, to actually read
I wouldn't win it, and I wouldn't be afraid of it
Satoshi Nakamoto wrote a paper that everybody in this class
If you were at MIT and a fewer viewer at Harvard
I'm telling you can read it
You'll understand maybe a half to two-thirds of it
It's not deeply technical
It's, and it's only 8 or 9 pages
I've also assigned National Institute of Science Technology
about 20 pages of reading from Nest
The question is whether that's Bitcoin
I'm going to skip through the study questions
but the study questions are really about cryptography
and how append only time stamping
We are going to get into the nitty gritty over three lectures
I couldn't commit the whole play, the course the whole semester
And but I think three lectures, Thursday and the two next week
anytime you want to come to see me
Sabrina is somewhere here, on the floor
Who's one of our Tas
is a computer science master student and knows more
about all of this. Madores, who was here last week
I don't know if Madores is here
He was part of the digital currency initiative
Over three lectures
We're going to try to work through
what's the cryptography and why is that matter
How does the time stamping happen
How does this look like money
And how do the transactions kept
Yes
You get to close it out, almost
Can you just answer the question posed about the longest running blockchain?
I can answer that
but the assignment was to answer it by Thursday, right?
So by Thursday
what's your first name?
Caroline
Did I say I was going to answer it today...
Oh did I say today？
No, is there a mutable record of what I said?
I'll answer it now if you want
But who... does anyone have the answer in the whole class?
Yeah. It's a service called Surety that Gillespie begun
begun working in 1995, was a time stamp
service for digital documents
And the way they did was use a hash function to create a seal
with a timestamp of the document
and then process the weekly batch of seals
And they actually published it in the New York Times in its homes
So Carolyn, is good to raise the question
I thought it was for Thursday
But thank you
Stewart Haber, a cryptographer
and a colleague at Bell Labs in the early 90s, said
how do we notarize information digitally notarize
And we're going to be talking about this Thursday a lot
They used a cryptographic method called hash functions
And they were just trying to notarize information
And by 1995, they took
they were entrepreneurs
They created a company called Surety
And once a week they publish in the New York Times
and they still do it
You can get a New York Times
I believe it's on Saturday or Sunday
and they take
it's in the classified section and they have the hash function
which you'll read about between now and Thursday
They have the hash of all the preexisting information
And so they time stamp it by using the New York Times
And they use cryptography
And it's currently 23 years and running
So that's the longest in terms of time
not the longest with how many ledgers, or how many...
Correct, because
Bitcoin is about 550000 blocks
And this would be whatever
23 years times 52 is,  longest in time
Thank you
I look forward to seeing you