The following content is provided under a Creative Commons license
Your support will help MIT Open courseware continue to offer high quality educational resources for free
To make a donation or to view additional materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT Open Courseware at OCW dot MIT dot e d U
I just want to say how touched I am that you are all still here
I really
you know
there's a lot of shopping opportunities in the MIT
Courses
And that you have come back and not shaken
Lewis
after reading Satoshi Nakamoto's
Peer to peer Bitcoin paper
Or maybe you just came back to see whether I was going to crash and burn describing it
But what we're going to try to do in the next three classes just to frame it is really give you some of the technical underpinnings of blockchain technology through the lens of Bitcoin
Bitcoin is just the first use case of blockchain technology
So if I often say Bitcoin
this or Bitcoin
that it's really largely not entirely largely applicable to blockchain technology
My feeling is I'm only about 8 or 9 months ahead of all of you
I may have spent my whole professional life around finance and public service
and I can talk a lot about markets and about public policy
But MIT has given me the gift of thinking about blockchain technology
And I'm trying to return that gift a little bit for you all
And I have a few computer scientists in the room that are gonna bail me out if I don't get this right
Sabrina
and then
oh
I see Elaine is putting up his
do you all know a lean
He's actually a Ph D student MIT computer science so
Somebody gets to that part of their life thinking
yeah
what
what was that terrible
terrible
like choice
Yeah
but he is going to bail us all out
But the reason that I think it's relevant not to just belabor it is I really believe the only way that any of us can get to ground truths is to know a little bit about how the inner workings of this technology are
You're not going to have to do an algorithm or actually do a hash function
but to know underneath it
And then you can step away and say I no longer need to know how the carburetor on the car works
But I know what a carburetor is or you know
whatever analogy you want
So with that little bit
as opposed to sort of all that Socratic code calling that I did last class because money
fiat currency is something at the core and ledgers is at the core of a Sloane students either education or background
This is a little less of the core if today's and the next couple of lectures
if you can work with me that I want you to interrupt me any time You've got a question
I'm not going to do much cold calling
so I don't want you to relax too much
I still want you to do the readings
the next three classes
but just raise your hand
Stop me say well
But what
What is that all about
And that is just so that we can work a little bit different on these
Next
classes
So as I've always gonna be doing consistency
what are the study questions
And so really
what are the design features
What are the key design features of this new technology
Blockchain
And I put a few on the syllabus
And we're gonna go through all this today
And next week
Cryptography
appendix only time stamps
blocks
distributed consensus algorithms and networking
I list later in this lecture
you'll see 8 or 10 that I guess it's 10 that we're going to really dig
dig into
Can I just get a sense of the class
And this is not first Toledo or Sabrina to write down notes about participation
Is it a decent assumption
Did did most of or all of you at least read Nakomoto paper
Alright
good
All right
great
Just a sense how many of you felt you got at least half of it
maybe less than two-thirds
but at least half of it
All right
Pretty good when I first read it
I was around with you
So it's alright
Elaine
you got more than half of it
right
I read it 5 years ago
So you read it 5 years ago
Yeah
Life choices talk
talk about it
And alright
And you're taking this class
Good
good
So we'll go through each of those
And then more specifically
we're going to peel back the cryptography
the two main cryptographic algorithms
or these words that you'll hear sometimes cryptographic primitives
I mean
what is a cryptographic primitive
Oh
it's a wild beast
Or so many of them now
But what's the two words to gather information
Well
that's what I'm saying
It could be
I mean
it could be a hash function
It could be an encryption function
It could be a verifiable complication scheme
It could be a data outsourcing fee
It could be a data access private
but it's anything that basically protects a communication and the presence of adversaries
Well
it's also something that you can use to prove that computation was done correctly on our untrusted server
So it's not just communication
corporate production
So communications and computation that needs to be protected or verified have some form of cryptographic algorithm
which happens to be called a cryptographic primitive
The two main ones
And there's a third one we'll talk about later in this semester
But the two main ones
hash function
just as a working knowledge of blockchain is worthy to know
And we're going to
we're going to get
everybody's gonna get there
We're going to all get there the way you have some sense of what a hash function is
And then this whole concept of digital signatures
which relates to asymmetric cryptography
Those two are very fundamental to blockchain technology
Later in the semester
we'll talk a little bit about zero knowledge proofs
but they're not as fundamental to the first application
And so that's why they're
you know
kind of
And they help making things verifiable and immutable
And that's the business side
The market side
Why does it matter otherwise
Like
who cares what's in the carburetor if it doesn't matter
And then how does this all relate to the double spend problem
I can call it Carlo
And on this visibility
do you remember what the double spend problem was from the it was when that they would use the same coin
I guess
And then use it in multiple places and other Linkedin
Cold digital wallets are pursued
So in essence
a double spend is when you have a piece of information and you use it twice
And we have to call this piece of information money
But you use it twice
You can send an email to two people
And that's okay
I mean
it's a little embarrassing if you're sending it to one friend telling them you are available for dinner
And the other friend thought you told him you weren't available
but you can still send it to two places
But in the system of money
it's a critical thing that you don't use it twice
The readings
Was the demo helpful
I mean
we're going to
we're going to do a lot more on the I watched that demo list November
December
It was one of the first things I watched from an MIT student
I don't know if you knew this Bosworth
and I found it very helpful
So I'm clear that
And I see it's actually that demo is on a Stanford blockchain course as well
So on the West Coast
one of our competitors is using an MIT product
And so we're gonna
we're going to just do a slight review of what we did in class 2
And then we're going to talk about the key design features
hash functions
As I mentioned
what is an append
Only log block headers and Merkel trees
an asymmetric cryptography and digital signatures
Crazy
we're gonna cover all five of those today
And then you're going to tell me how we did
Oh
Bitcoin addresses
which is just a small thing
Six
actually
like
so last time for those of you that work with us
we talked about money
And again
money is just a social construct or an economic consensus mechanism
We're going to talk a lot about consensus next Tuesday when we talk about the consensus protocol in Bitcoin
But remember
money itself is just a consensus
There was a question on Tuesday
I think a lean actually had asked this question about
but what does it mean to be a liability of the central bank
Why is money
What does that actually mean
And I said it just means that somebody else will accept it
It's a social consensus because it's not that they're going to give you anything else
It's just that you can get a bank deposit
You can pay your taxes
You can use it at Starbucks if in fact
you've already gotten a cup of coffee
If you remember
it's only legal tender for a debt and so forth
See
up
Money is just in that long line
But it's had its challenges and stabilities
It doesn't mean it's going to go away
I'm not a Bitcoin
Maximum lesson thinks that fiat currencies are going to go away
but fiat currencies have their instability is particularly around the world
A weak monetary policy
In essence
when you debase a currency and allow a lot of it to be issued or are usually around unstable fiscal policy
So either the government is spending a lot
The king is off to foreign wars and the bank of England was actually set up in the late 17th century
in essence
to control the currency when the king was of England
I think it was in wars with France
If I can recall a lot of banks
center banks were set up right about when a sovereign was was off
debasing a currency and spending too much at war
and I think that the ledgers we talked about ledgers
how critical ledgers are
In essence
ledgers are a way to keep records
and those records could either be transaction records or balanced records
We'll see that Bitcoin is set up as a transaction ledger later
We're going to be talking about other blockchain technologies that are set up as balanced ledgers
So one should not just think immutably that there's only one way to do this
but transactions and ledgers are at the core of Bitcoin
And central banking is
of course
built on ledgers
The master ledger of the central bank
And then the commercial banks have sort of the subledgers
And then you can think sometimes your digital wallet
maybe Starbucks has yet a third tier ledger
We obviously live in an electronic age already
We know this
There has been many efforts
They've all died until Bitcoin to crack that riddle that we talked about
peer to peer money without a central authority
And later in the semester when we talk about
What are the use cases
That's gonna be the core thing
And why
I'm not a Maximus
I'm not sure
In every circumstance
essential with intermediary isn't necessarily so bad
And this is not a value judgment
This is just pure money and markets and so forth
But in some circumstances
decentralization really will compete and beat the centralized intermediary
So let's talk about his little paper
which of course
he was modest or she was modest
Please remind me
we don't know who Nakamoto is is or was or a group of people
I've been working on a new electronic cash system that's fully peer-to-peer with no trusted third party
So you've seen this slide before
but a time stamped a patent only law
Just think blocks of data
you know
to kind of oversimplify
But it's got a name
blockchain technology
And I don't think that Satoshi paper
you all read it in the last few days
I
of course
read it again yesterday just to make sure I remembered it was
I don't remember that he ever used the word blockchain
Am I right about that
So the words blockchain really have been sort of layered over his innovation
So information blocks going on
And that leads to basically a database
But it's the blocks of data
Bitcoin right now is about 550000 blocks
And the blocks are added on average every 10 minutes
And we'll talk about why it's every 10 minutes
And not only why Satoshi Nakomoto made it every 10 minutes
but how they maintain that other blockchains like Ethereum
It's about every 7 seconds
so don't get too caught up that it's all the same thing
And there are some technologists here
Sylvia McCully is working on algorithm
And that's even tighter
less than 7 seconds
So there's not one way
There's multiple designs on how often blocks are at it
But let's start with Bitcoin secured by
Yes
guess what
Those two cryptographic primitives
hash functions
and digital signatures
We lose anybody yet
Yeah
maybe
And then there's a consensus for agreement
The whole debate
usually about databases is who gets to change the data
And this is true in all databases
In essence
it's usually centralized
but in blockchain
it's all of a sudden
well
maybe it's not centralized
Who gets to add that next bit of information
The next block and the consensus agreement is which we'll discuss next Tuesday is about that very issue
And I think there was a little pretty picture that I've done in slides before
but I'm going to
I'm going to delay that discussion until next Tuesday
And hopefully you all come back
So what are the key features
And I might do a little cold call
Like
do you remember any key feature tub and from from the papers
Hopefully
All right
I mean
you have the hash function or hash and any other key features
Let's see how many I'm going to have 10 on this page
Up on that
On a public key
What is that
Private public key
Private and public kid
Yes
so a symmetric cryptography or private and public kid
hash functions
Yes
private public kid
And the other kind of key design features or or words you didn't understand
Maybe that's another way to put it
Liam drove the dresses with a address of the three point addresses
That's four of the things this is going well
Rehab the payments
So payment is
is something that is trying to address
It's not really a design feature
but it's a
they have a solution for double payments
I'll give you a credit for it
But it's
all right
So Hugo says miners
which is really the consensus
So I'll
I'll say that the design feature is the consensus or proof of work
Kelly
the full number of verses of light
So you
right
So very interesting
This concept of nodes and Satoshi actually talks about full nodes or lightweight nodes
In essence
how much information has to be stored
I want to reserve that
Kelly
Please remind me when we talk about blockheaded us to come back to that
But nodes and the network is a very important design feature over here
Restructure the Merkel tree structure
So Merkel tree structure is a way to compress a lot of data and the and also to sort through that data
Oh
oh
no
Supreme is not going to clean me down here
Merkel tree structure is there
We're gonna talk about that
Two more like the notes
What's that
The notes
What are the notes
All right
What's that
Knots
knots
The knots
Okay
so a knots
Anybody know what the word nonsense
A year ago
This is it
So we're all getting there
Look
do I have a look
Do you know what a nonsense
In the actual protocol
it's essentially a guess for the miners to
So the word not means a random number that is used once and for a number
And once it's a number that's random
And it's used once
But that's how I've learned it
And so one more because it's sort of this is great
Remind me of your first name
Crea
Crea peer here
All right
so how
This is what I have cryptographic hash functions
And we're going to go through these in more detail times stamped append only logs the block headers and Merkel trees
Some Merkel trees were discussed
but we need to actually say what
what information is kept at the head of the block as opposed to all the but the body and some of that's just to make it more manageable
A symmetric cryptography
which is this public key
private key and signature
the Bitcoin addresses themselves
which interestingly
are a little bit different than public keys
And then I breach break because the next we're going to talk about next Tuesday
the proof of work
the miners
the nodes
the nonsense are all in that
Little topic
There's actually in Bitcoin
A really important protocol is how information gets propagated on the internet
Just the network communication
It's not written about a lot
You won't read a lot about it in the thamiel poppers
digital gold or all the other popular books
but it is an important thing to remind ourselves that information has to propagate around the Internet and all these transactions have to communicate with each other
There's currently about 10000 nodes on the Bitcoin network
We don't know where all the all of them are
but they're probably in 180 different countries
And so it just also the networking and communication matters
And it matters to the economics a lot
There's a native currency
And this is interesting
That was the one thing that no one said that's in the actual technological design feature
It's not only that he created a currency
but the native currency is part of the economic incentive system for
And we'll have some fun with that
In essence
he said that when you mind and did the proof of work you created and you got some native currency called Bitcoin
So he created an economic incentive system
whomever Satoshi Nakamoto was or is knew a lot about economics as well as technology
Yes
I just wanted to quickly add to what you said
So it's not only that you create this native currency
but once the finite supplies reach
the currency can be distributed as a transaction fee
which I think is a very important and intense rise
And remind me your first name
Daniel
So what Daniel just said is
is really interesting
not only to take light of this individual individuals that did this
but this world of Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies creates a unit of of account that could be valued
And once it's valued
you have sort of a native currency
But as Daniel said
Nakamoto also said
there would be a finite limit
It happens to be 21 million
Bitcoin is the most
It can be
And we'll get there around the year 2040
Does anyone know how many Bitcoin they were
Right now
About half of you were reinvesting
And that's what I was kind of curious you go about 17 million Bitcoin right now
and all 17 million have come from this process of proof of work and mining
Initially
it was 50 Bitcoin every 10 minutes
roughly every 10 minutes
Then
it went down to 25
And we are now at 12
5 Bitcoin
And does anyone know what today's value purported
I always should say
purported value of Bitcoin cuz I don't know if we can trust some of those websites that say what the values are
what
what is it
So $6500 a Bitcoin
a 12
5 Bitcoin to mine a block
So you
so you see that it's about $80000 is the reward to mine a block
right
So
so there he created an incentive system that initially
if you got 50 Bitcoin and they weren't worth a penny
you would not commit that much
You had
you had to be a hobbyist basically in 29 or a cyber punk or just kind of curious because you weren't getting much incentive if in fact
it's worth 6500 a day
you're getting $80000
If you actually successfully mine a block
and then there's the transaction inputs and outputs
Think about
a check
You know who signs it where you move
There's something called the unspent transaction ledger
So this is the ledger part
So when you think I think of the technology
I think of cryptography
which is kind of all that stuff at the top
which we're going to discuss today
Secondly
the consensus mechanism
in essence
that's that key question of any database
Who gets to amend the database
Who gets to decide to change the state of what we all agreed to
And then
thirdly
is the ledger or the transaction ledger
which we're not going to deep dive into the scripting language
But we are next Thursday Going to talk a little bit about the underlying scripting
So does that give you a payoff
It's all this cryptography the consensus
and then the transactions
Yes
I don't understand if you're going to use this person
Oh
you can just curious
So you mentioned that is a very special day
Alright
alright
So just curiosity
You mentioned that the
per block value is roughly $80000 as of as of now
So just curious
In terms of the CPU power
the electricity that will be consumed to Minecraft
How much does that translate into equivalent in US dollar terms
So the question that's asked is how much
electricity is being consumed for that minor to get that reward
that $80000
And I'm going to try to answer in one minute
But we'll come back to this later in the semester about the economics and blockchain
economics and mining economics
But what has happened over these 10 years is more and more computers that are being used are are trying to mine for the Bitcoin
And so today
in the most recent research I have seen is that the probability of winning a block
There's so much is it measured in terror hashes
I can't remember the numbers
but it's how many times Tara hashes
which is
is it
15 zeros
Is it Tara hash
Is it trackers at 12
You know
Well
in an event
there's so many hashes being done
A second X number of terror hashes that your probability of winning is quite low
And so what's happened is most nodes and miners have entered into agreements called mining pools
where they smooth out the risk
And everybody shares in the rewards
But those economics will talk about later
It's thought to be that you need electricity cost around 3 cents a kilowatt hour to be successful
And in most parts of the world
you can't get electricity for 3 cents a kilowatt hour
So you would put your mining rigs where you can get low cost electricity or a where you possibly can
You could get it legally low cost or illegally low cost
So there
there are a lot of mining rigs and in jurisdictions where there may be local officials that are allowing those mining rigs and instead of 3 cents a kilowatt hour to the electric company
it's 1 to 2 cents a kilowatt hour to the local government officials
So
and the two largest mining pools are in China
And the third is in Russia
But we'll get into the sort of the economics
And at least some theories about why summer where they are so cryptography
So eileen's probably going to clean me up
It's not just communication in the presence of an adverse series
It's also computation in the presence of adverse series is that that would be good
And we talked about
we're not going to deep
deep dive
if you remember
even in ancient times
if you were going to war
there was this wonderful little way that you could do cryptography
And then anybody who's seen imit
imit imitation games
Yeah
about the British
you know
breaking into the German codes
even though they should have probably given more credit to the Polish government that had probably broken into it in the 1930s
but touring did a great work
And then we're gonna talk about asymmetric cryptography
Okay
what is a hash function
A hash function
And that these are just words that I think of it
I think of it as a fingerprint for data
But it has certain properties
the one that you'll see throughout is that it takes inputs of input x
it maps that input of any size to a fixed size
So one that we use here in the us
one hash function
we all uses zip codes in a way
5 digits
It's a fixed size
I know i'm doing this as a loose hand
You know
How can I think of it
But zip codes you might have 50000 people or 5000 people all living in one in one postal district
and you can map them to zip codes
And it's a to fixed Led
Now
I don't know whether my friends in the computer science departments
but
but it's an early sense of a hash function
I just wanted to say there are
there are tangible things in our life that act like hash functions problem with zip codes is it will not in any way be a secure hash function
And you'll see that in a minute
But it does take
you can be a £300 person or a £30 kid
and you still map into the same zip code
It's deterministic
It's always the same
So if you take a certain set of data
it will always give you the same hash and that's relevant to the background
And you can efficiently compute it
You don't want to take a year to do this
You've got to do it in short periods of time
And in Bitcoin's case
it's done in nanoseconds or less because there one computer 1 CPU can do can't remember probably how many millions a second couple of terror hashes a second
A couple of terror house hashes a second
So it's a remarkably efficient algorithm
And so a bunch of mathematicians and hashing started in the 1950 S and 60 S
But the ones that we're talking about here are much more recent
But it's really terrifically talented scientists
mathematicians computer scientists and sometimes the national institute standards of technology here in the us
working on hash functions
So it takes an array of any size
puts it into a fixed number
I think zip codes for a minute
It's deterministic
It's always you only live in 1 zip code
in a sense
And it's very efficient
But now what are the cryptographic properties because a zip code wouldn't make it just wouldn't
Well
the computer scientist uses term preimage resistant
I would just say it's one way out
You can only go one way
meaning it's infeasible
And to determine the input from the output
it's infeasible to determine the ax from the hash of x
Does anybody know why I use the word infeasible rather than impossible
It will be in the first name is very different
So because you can do it with blue posts
So you might be able to use it
Brute force
What do you mean by brute force
Just so everybody try all options and try all options and
But as I understand it
a sort of tentative cryptography for centuries is not to have it mathematically impossible
It's the point is getting it so and infeasible that your adversary is can't either get the communication or so forth
So hash functions
I just say this because you can't assume that Bitcoin can't be broken
We all call it immutable
It is immutable until the hash functions that are inside of Bitcoin might be broken
And even Satoshi wrote about this in 2010
He got emails
There's this wonderful book
If any of you want that I mentioned in the bookshelf at the end of the syllabus said
well
what if a Shaw 2 56
Which is the hash function gets broken
And his answer was
was
well
there will be a better hash function at that time
Whatever that is
will hash the entire system
whatever that is
Because remember
you can take something of any size
hash it with the new system and move forward
And so he felt he or she felt in this wonderful email is that Bitcoin actually could transition to a new hash function as long as you had a little bit of time before it was all corrupted
Okay
so this one is our code called the gamer problem
Is that what you're describing
The gamblers ruin problem
the probability that an attacker could catch up to like recreating it
No
no
that's something else
That's
that's a really sweet one in the matter
Yeah
so that's the
if I can call correctly
you know
you wanna sort of assess how hard it is at the 4th
5th coin
If I have a lot of computational power
how hard is it for me to create a fork
And so those she doesn't analysis at the end of the paper
Oh
oh
I apologize
You're talking about in his paper
Yes
in his paper
he's talking about how hard it is computationally to do what some people call a 51% attack to basically take over all the nodes
And that part of his paper
we're going to talk about next Tuesday
But it's basically
can you take over the nodes
I was talking about a separate thing
Can you break the cryptography
And he doesn't write about that In his paper
He writes about it in an email about 10 months later or so
Second key cryptographic thing
So we said one is it's one way the other thing is this concept of collision resistant
I presume if everybody in this room told me that your birthdays
there's multiple people in this room who have the same birthday
And in fact
if we got it passed
26 people in a room
it's over 50% chats that two of you have the same birthday
We don't need to get to 183 people in the room
which is half of the days of the year
We can get to about 26 or 7
And
similarly
the key thing is
is that two sets of data are
it's again infeasible that x and Y would hash to the same thing
It's not impossible
It is infeasible
And if you look at the history of hash functions
this is usually the thing that at some point in time
these hash functions will not be collision resistant
Some quantum computing will come along or something will come along
But for now
you can put something of any size in
and they're independent
They also look terribly random
It's called an avalanche effect
meaning you change one little difference
And the whole thing looks different
So when you noticed on that little video
if you changed one thing
it all looks so different
And why that's important is it makes it more secure
And then there's something called puzzle friendliness
even if you know a little bit of the input
it doesn't mean that you're going to get the output
I put these up here
not for you to know them
You're not going to get tested if you go into business as a law
And you've started when you probably haven't thought
well
you know
collision resistant this or that
But I just wanted you to know there are always a bunch of cryptography underneath
And
the keys
It is not 100 percent immutable
It's like probably one
And
you know
I don't know
1 quadrillion immutable
but there's still these things could be broken
And quantum computing and something else might Elaine
the actual probability should be actually one over two to the power of one 28th
It's much more than 1 quadrillion
So
so it's 1 over 10 to about the 40th
How did I do my math
All right
alright
and anybody who is interested can come to office hours
Well
so it's highly unlikely to be broke in
but I think it's always worth while to say
well
no
there there is some outward
It's not as bounded as you think
So what
What is it used for in many places
It's used for names and references and pointers
and something called commitments in Bitcoin
It's used for pointers because one block points to another block
But it's also used in commitments
You'll hear these words
We're not going to delve into them
but the headers and the Merkel trees use something called Shaw 2 56
which is a standard
which is literally 256 b long
That's like zeroes and ones for 256 registries
But a Bitcoin address
actually
So Satoshi Nakamoto threw in a loop
I'm glad to debate why
But he uses two hash functions for Bitcoin addresses
And the one thing I saw that he actually wrote about it is he said if one of them was broken
at least the other one is less likely to be broken
So it was
as I've read about it
I think in his own voice
you have to hash something twice
And he was just making it that much more secure
even though Eileen
there was one out of 10 to the 40th chance
which is astronomically low
So
right
so remember
where's Caroline
I don't remember
Here we are
You asked me about
I thought I'd set it up for today
but you were good to remind me for Tuesday
What's the longest running hash
A time stamp hash
Is a great question
thank you for the compliments
The answer is
yeah
I don't
I
we already have medically
so I'm not sure if I'm totally butchering this one
but it came out of Dell Labs
The Stewart paper is a shorty area is the
yeah
so Hebrew and his
his colleague
Yes
you got it
roommate
That's your room at terrific
So
I'm just trying to say it wasn't Bitcoin that had it
He did this in 1991
But by 1995
they started a company called Surety
I don't think it took off that much
It's not competing with Apple for the largest market cap or anything like that
Or Facebook
But every week in the notices section
you can see a hash literally that there's a
it's time stamped because it's in the New York Times
And it's a hash that all those funky digits and everything of all the information came before it
And they're basically hashing any document
any document that you want a time stamp in that week
you put it in one follows another
and that's a blockchain
It's not about money
There's no native currency
and so forth
I believe that Heber and Ster
Netta are three of the eight or 9 footnotes in the Satoshi paper
Maybe it's four of them
So he gets his credit
And if you go to his website stored Hebrew
I think he says a blockchain's cofounder on his personal website here now
So here we get this was in the National Institute
the NIST paper
But timestamp dependent only logs in Bitcoin or blockchain
What is put together is the header
the top information
And if I can go past the visual and just say
what's there
There's five pieces of key information
the version
It doesn't change that often
but there is a version number one
the previous blocks hash
So it's some information about all the blocks that came before it
The Merkel route hash
Which does anybody want to tell me what that does the Merkel route
Scratch
so it doesn't really push the transactions in the bottommost layer of the tree and then create the fee of hashtag each of the transaction
So if I
if I go back to the this
this nice little picture
the yellow boxes
the bottom of each of these blocks is all the transactions
There could be upwards to 1000 2000 transactions in a bloc
So this blockchain concept
1000 2000
there's means and methods well before
nakamoto's paper about how to compress that
how to keep that information a little bit tidier
And that uses this thing called Merkel roots
The thing
the five items right at the top
the what's called the block header doesn't have the thousand transactions
And earlier
Kelly
you had asked me about full nodes and light nodes
A light node or a wallet that anyone here could a download on your cell phone probably does not download the millions of transactions that have happened in the history of Bitcoin
You are unlikely to download what's called a full node
but you might download all the headers
This bit of information
That's all of the headers
all of the information in Bitcoin is still not that large
It's less than 200 gigs
But the all of the headers
I think
is single digit gigs
I can't remember if it's 4 or 6 GB right now
What is the number is 80 bites
So it's in the bytes times 500000
which is 50 MB
60 MB of feathers
So 60 MB
So it's much smaller as as opposed to like 180 gig
So Satoshi was thinking in advance
And every blockchain that you're going to work on
likely
I mean
there might be some that this concept of it's really keeping the security by a little bit of information in something called a header and then pushing all the meat of the transaction and data down
And this is really important when you get to like Ethereum
where there is a lot of data and a lot of computation down in each of these blocks
it's sort of like if stored Hebrew
Had a lot of documents and pictures and everything
He didn't
You don't have to have all the picture quality and a whole movie
You can actually hash a whole movie and you still get these 256 b
And so
oops
So the header has the previous hash
this Merkel route
which is just a way to get all the transactions
Just think of a Merkel route as a way to grab 2000 transactions in a way and a time stand
That one's easy
We can get that difficulty to target
Does anybody know what what
Blockchain Bitcoin tried to do to make it more or less difficult over time and now a broader sweep here go more to fill the retirement such that stays with you can block every 10 minutes
So with more computational power
my block
So as far you find a block
the more miners there are
So every block header needs to have some what's called a difficulty target
How difficult is the mining going to be since we're talking about mining next Tuesday
Please all bring me back to difficulty to target
And then what's a Nance
What's that
A random number that's used once number 1
nuts
And that's
that's hash functions
How do we do
They are a little off the skids
We are
Should be the number of characters in the house
She needs it
The output
not the input
No
no
For the number of characters
And you have still limited
right
So right
A pool of options that you have
but you have many
many transactions starts like a flow
right
So actually
you're just consuming and consuming hashtag up to the point where you are gonna repeat the hash
right
Spargo
No
what to say
How should you have to keep your premium for random to which information you are referring
So
could you help me pronounce your first name
Just to Jiang has asked the right question
He's saying
well
how do you know
Especially as you have more and more time and more and more time
you might get the same output of a hash from different inputs
And if you recall
Wait
somebody does recall now before brutish in front of brutish
I mean
yeah
the papers imagine that it like it's possible that too
like
like the ash of X
you go to ash of Y
but it's if like
the miners are working
like
not at the same time
And if like
the same information is not treated at the same exact time
it won't be a problem because then like
you just continue
I'm just like two different
So you're correct
As it relates to mining
But there is another piece of it as well
Is that the hash function
if it's a good cryptographic secure hash function is what's called collision resistant
where what you're saying is so infeasible
In fact
one divided by 10 to the 40th
You know
that's a 1 with 40 zeros after it
It's so infeasible to have it
It's possible
but infeasible to have it
What you're referencing is
is what if two parties solve the cryptographic puzzle as opposed to a collision
And because the difficulty they just got it at the same time
quiz
it seemed like a dumb question
But now there's no dumb questions
Coming back
timestamp
So attributed
So is it from the whole system
So time stamps are not a particularly important part of Bitcoin
They are timestamped
but sometimes if somebody puts something off and it's off by a few minutes or even up to 2 hours
there's a
there's a check in the technology and the scripting function
If the time staffs off more than a couple hours
So literally
it's not of that precise
Having said that the real way that time stamping happens is if if a block is mined and it's the 540 thousandth block
And it's sort of accepted in all the nodes
these 10000 nodes start mining the 540000
And first block of that
In essence
it's just
I think
of it as almost like a stack
And so what's
in essence
more relevant than the actual time that's in the header
And they all have a timestamp in the header
But what's more relevant is the order of the blocks
And most importantly
the previous block hash
Yes
I hadn't say that
Without the time stamp
you cannot do this difficulty readjustment
The pineapple is very important
If you don't have pineapple to the block
you cannot do the difficulty adjustment
which is necessary to keep the rate of bucks 10 minutes
I'm gonna partially agree with you because the difficulty adjustment happens every two weeks
So even if any one individual or five or six time stamps are a little goofed up in the two weeks
the algorithm is basically looking over the course of about 2000 blocks
So
so a little good stuff is fine
It's fine
But you need the timestamp
You need it
Time stamps
But it's
and it's more important is basically the
yeah
I'll go back a slide
It's the order of the blocks
And please
so we have to legends
The paper didn't really go into detail
but it said like in addition to how unlikely it is with like to the parliament 29th
But even if there were two that hashed to the same kind of posh digest that
it would be unlikely it would be valid in the context
So like
what's about blockchain transaction with that to reduce the likelihood of any problems
which there was a lot of detail into why like the blockchain parts to be conscious even more unlike
I want to hold that question for Tuesday
but it has to do with rather than the collision issue
What the papers talking about is if two miners solved the puzzle pieces
and that doesn't mean that they got identical hashish because the puzzle is not geared to getting an exact hash
The Bitcoin puzzle is having a certain number of leading zeros
So it's literally
it started
I think it was 9 or 10 leading zeros
I'm talking about 10 years ago
And now you have to hash to something with
I think it's about 20 or 26
Leading zeroes are meaning it's gotten more and more difficult
And the result of the hash has to have a bunch of leading zeros
What you saw in that video
I'm sorry
I have a question on like how the hash does not gonna do
Tash comes about
So if it's only if it's only hashing the transactions
how does it change when the hash of the previous blog changes
Okay
so idiot it
it reminds me of that old television
So Johnny Carson
and you just did a great setup for the comedian
So thank you
So I'm going to go to Merkel roots
So Merkel roots
which are binary binary data tray
looks something like this
If one had 1000 transactions
I wouldn't have a pretty slide
So this only goes to four levels
But think of four transactions at the bottom
right
They're each hashed
And then you can catch me
You put the two hashes together
You hash that you keep going up the tray
If you had 1000 transactions
because that's tuitive a 10th
roughly
then you'd have 10 levels of this tray
And so that's what happens
And literally the mining pool operators are doing this a lot for the nodes
But in the bitcoin and core application in the
in the software that anybody in this room could download the software
If you wish
There is software that helps takes transactions
puts them basically into this binary tree called a Merkel tree
uses hash functions and basically skinnies it all the way up to the top is that I think what my question was was that if if the structure like
given that the structure exists
how does the root hash change with the previous block
So basically
based on the video that if you change the hash of the previous block
all the blocks forward
will get invalidated because the hash changes
but it doesn't seem to use the previous hash
So I'm gonna repeat the question does a Merkel root for that is basically a summary of the 10000 transactions that are in a block
Change it if the rest of the header changes or the previous block change
and the answer is no one
it only changes if some of the data in the 10000 transactions changes
And so a Merkel route will change if you put different transactions in the mix or as is really important
One of the incentives
you get your 12
5 Bitcoins today in what's called a Coinbase transaction
And so one of these thousand transactions is the same
The payment to the miner
So the Merkel route would be different depending upon who wins
But that wasn't your question
I'm just saying
But Merkel roots are a very efficient way to take thousands of transactions
Store it up
have one spot
Police
so the order of the different transaction has to be exactly the same for everyone that is hashing
right
No
actually not
So if you're hashing and you're running a mining rig and Alonzo running a mining rig
if a line solves the puzzle and propagates it out on the network and people start mining on top of a lion's block because they say
well
he's finished
you're not
You're just going to probably start mining on the top of this block and look in something called the mem pool
The memory pool is in this network of all the free floating transactions
You'll scoop up the next set of transactions
And so can how can we validate that all the transactions And he wrote
are the real ones
All right
so validation
which is
which is more next Thursday
But I'll give it a shot
No
no
It's a good question
Every transaction
Or actually
you're setting me up digital signatures
There you go
Thank you
Did you have a question
Or I'm going to go ahead
And do so the second cryptographic thing
And we're going to keep going back and forth
Hash functions are basically a way to compress
A lot of data
Have a fingerprint
Make sure that it's basically commitment
Digital signatures
Well
remember that little graph that we had
Alice and Bob
Alice wants to send a note to Bob and just say hello
Bob
She wants to encrypt it
She encrypts it with Bob Public Key
Send it to him
He decrypts it with his private key
You might say
oh my God
Ganesler what's a private key
What's a public key in cryptography
It's a way to kind of scramble information
I know I'm really making this like
but it it
So if we went back to that little mechanism
the Romans used or were used with the Germans used in the Enigma machine
They were symmetric cryptography
Both people had the key
The key was the Enigma machine with five roaders in the 1970 S
Some wonderful technologist here elsewhere basically said
well
what if the key isn't the same because the adversary could steal the key
What if it's not symmetric
But it's asymmetric
There's a private key and a public key
In essence
there's two keys that have some mathematical relationships and the math between these two keys don't matter for a class like this
but know that the public key and the private key link together
they're bonded together
But the critical thing is about digital signatures
There's three functions
You have to generate a key pair
And when a key pair is generated
a public key and a private key are generated at the same time
and they need a random number to go into it
And one of the things that makes a lot of Bitcoin and other wallets insecure
And it's probably why some have been hacked
The wallets
not Bitcoin is because they don't have good random number generation
Yes
brutish
I saw I was at a conference last week where a technologist from University of Pennsylvania had done a survey of 150 hedge funds
mining companies and Bitcoin wallet companies and the like
So they actually let a cyber security individual get inside and do a survey of 150
which you would consider really committed high end users of Bitcoin miners and hedge funds
And crypto exchange is
And it was horrifying
Their cyber security as to how they're what they're doing with their private keys before even got to the private keys
Many of them didn't really have a secure way to create the random numbers to create their private keys
And so it's just a piece when somebody says they have really good private key public key in the back
your mind
Just no
there's got to be some way to do a random number generation
That's the only math that I'm going to ask you to remember about
There is a signature function
And the key thing is a signature creates
You can create a digital signature from a message and a private key
So if Kelly has a private kid and wants to send a secret message to somebody across the room
Isabella
you want a message from Kelly
Kelly is gonna take the message
You got this
Kelly
you're going to take the message and you're gonna sign it with a private K
You send it over to Isabella
How's the Elizabeth now
That is from you
She has to decrypt it
She's got to verify it
So there's a function called a verification function
And it comes back just
yes
no
I mean
it might say it's differently
but it's a just a yes
No
it's a verification function
Isabella
you want to do this with me is going to verify your signature is valid for this message
And because you have the public K
so you're right
Isabella has your public key
But using your public case
she can verify that the signature
It's magical math
but it's not magical math
It's real math
But it's not math
We need to study in this class
Yes
Hugo
that to generate any cute hair
Yeah
So they're both generated from the random number or like the privacy is not determined by the public here
The pup
You can think of it
In Bitcoin
it uses an elliptic curve cryptography
And you can think of it
Is that the private key is based on the random number
It's based it to me
more technical
It's the
the random number is what gets you to the public key
But I think of it as the private keys
almost the random number
And then the public key is generated along with it
You can have it on
Yes
so when you pick around the number actually become 0 and 2 to the 2 56 that are probably to pick a public key
You derive it directly from the private key
In fact
all you do is you exponentiate another number by your private kit
And
so it's
you can think of the public key as a one way function of the private key
So given a public key
you cannot recover the private key
If you could
then you could sign which one can be disastrous
And instead of exponentiation in Bitcoin
it uses
and it costs a function called the elliptic curve
But so what properties
And these are the key economic properties
as well as cryptographic properties
Basically
it's infeasible
And again
I use the word infeasible
I didn't say impossible
even though Eileen might want to tell me that it's whenever 10 to the 40th or something
but it's infeasible to find a private key from a public key to reverse engineer Sil
So even if you can't find the private key
like in the case of Kelly and Isabella and I knew Kelley's public key
could I send a message to Isabella impersonating Kelly
You need to do a signature
If you please just run your eye up there to do a digital signature
you need a private key and a message
And it's a function of the message and the private key by sir
Let's call it complex math
That digital signature was created from the private key
And the public key was created from the private key
And to oversimplify the reason that the verify function works is because both the digital signature is and the public key that Isabella has
Isabella has this digital signature
and she has the public key
And she has the message
The math is such that basically the private key
if you wish
almost like factors out
you know
you
but it think of two functions
She's got the Isabella has kelley's publicly the message
the digital signature
it either verifies or it doesn't
but she never has to see the private key
And in fact
Kelly does not want her to ever see the private key
Eric
Maybe just to simplify that the way the validation of a digital signature works as Katie's
Is run through a hash function which generates a house and is encrypted with current private
Then the message are encrypted and the C digital signature goes to Isabella
Isabella
What she does is uses the same hash function to run it with to generate the heart function and uses the public here of Kelly to unencrypt the signature and compare those to with those two hatches correspond
That means that if the message belongs to Kelly and it hasn't been tampered with
So that's the more or less simplification of the digital signature of the well
I don't know the so
So I mean
the key is basically that there's a scheme unrelated to Bitcoin that exists for many other reasons on the Internet
Many other reasons in commerce and in war that this public key
private key cryptography
And it's not simply just going back
it's not just simply Alice sending something
It's also digital signatures
You generate the keypair
everything in Bitcoin
everything in Ethereum has key pairs
public key and private key a digital signature
But Kelly never lose your private too
You got that
Do not
And by the way
you have to create it with a good random number generator because most sophisticated hedge funds around the world aren't
So you're going to be better than those
That's what I learned at a conference I was at recently
And then there's a verification function
a quick question about the random number generator
and the verification function
So is there any like third party generating the generator or the generator is like a function already existing
And like already there
it's a lot of
So
So the question is
is if random number generation is so important
are there outside parties that have good software in essence to produce the random number generation
And the answer is yes
And there's some that are not so good
And yes
some good laptops have it
At the heart
I want to skip ahead
Elliptic curve digital signature algorithm
That's the actual algorithm that Bitcoin uses to take the private K and so forth
But many of the wallets
if you
if you download a wallet application to hold your Bitcoin to hold your light coin to hold some other coin
that wallet application has a lot
a random number generation software
I can attest to all the random number generation software
I'm not a cybersecurity
expert
but there's probably a range of some that are a little bit more
There are stronger ones
The key to random number generation is if you're generating any lengths that it truly is not clumpier that that I would say it's what maximum entropy
you know
and that you really don't have any clumps if it all clumps in one area
then that's not great randomness
So I just want to finish because there's one other thing we're going to chat about to lay the groundwork is Bitcoin addresses
I put that up
You can look at the slides later
The details don't matter much
But the key thing is
is that when you hear somebody talk about public keys and Bitcoin addresses
colloquially
we all reference them the same
They're actually not the technology that Nakamoto did
was he uses the public key
He literally hashed it twice once with with this program
this hash function called shot 2 56
Another hash function then concatenates and puts a little check sum at the end and then uses something called a base 58 to make it even shorter
I've gone back and read some of nakamoto's emails for the two years after he published all this
and I've read other things
My understanding is is the reason there's two hash functions and actually two different lines was just to make everything a bit more secure
Also
a public key is a very long
It's about 512 b
And so you can shrink the data and make the data more compressed by hashing it
which took it to 256 b
He hashes it twice
And then he does it as base 58
That makes it even a little tighter
So for all purposes
you can go ahead and just use public key
And Bitcoin address is the same
But remember
back in the mind
Oh
actually
there are
there are little different
And Bitcoin addresses are a little bit more secure
supposedly
And less
of course
somebody's hacked into your wallet and figured out all these little details
A Bitcoin address is a little bit like the signatures on these notes we talked about
right
Remember what
And half of you don't use checking accounts
but these are early forms of checks
And there's a signature on the bottom that's really kind of a Bitcoin address that I'm sorry
The signature is the digital signature
the address
the Bitcoin address is who it's paid for
And I promise last slide
we're going to be talking about this next week
Transactions
all that stuff that rolls up into the Merkel trees
all that little
Anybody important
They basically have an input and an output
the input and a lot of time
But the input is a previous transaction
This uniquely identifies basically money
And you're going to send value in Satoshis
He named the unit of account for himself
There's a lot of Satoshis and everyone Bitcoin
That's why we don't hear much about Satoshis
But there's 10 to the 8th Satoshis and every one Bitcoin
So when you actually enter in the computer code and a transaction
you're doing it in Satoshis
And it's sent to a public key
That's a coin
That is what the incentive systems all about
Any other questions
And this was just that
I know it was a lot
I wonder how many of you are gonna come back on Thursday
No
let me
let me say this
It's not just that we're at MIT
but we are at MIT
Come on
Everybody in this room can get these kind of key concepts
The key questions that we talked about were Time stamp to pet and only logs
Is anybody want to tell me what a time
What if this class here in the next 7 minutes can get these two concepts
That's all we talked about for the last hour
So
I don't know your name in the orange shirt
What's that
Cambridge
Andrew
What's time
Append only logs time
Snap a pen
Delay logs is essentially a record of transactions or a block is blockchain uses it
with a time
And that can't be changed in the future
So you can only add on transaction
So it's kind of immutable because of all this cryptography is Stuart Haber was making it in a time stamped a pet and only log
And he was placing it where
Carolyn
you still with me
Where was Haver putting it out
New York Times
There you go
In the classified sections
So it just
it's a bunch of blocks of data compressed up
So we talked about something called Merkel trees and Merkel roots just think about it
That's a way to take a lot of information and compress it
but also make it searchable later because 1000 transactions when we talk next week
you have to be able to verify
Somebody asks me about how to verify
right
Okay
when you go back to verify
you need an index number to find it out in that Merkel tree situation and it's secured through hash functions
Anybody want to tell me the easiest lay definition of a hash hash function
Jennifer
it's like a map
The lozo members can step to just one
right
You could take a picture of this classroom and everybody exactly
And they could map into something
I don't know what a QR code
Be a form of a hash
Not cryptographically secure
but is it a
Is it a hash somewhere with different representation for some data rather than binary
You are using
All right
so I failed that one
It didn't
It often stores actually
So cryptographic hash function is a way to take not only a lot of information and put it into a fixed form
But the key thing here is the hash functions are what tie the blocks together
Because hash functions can point to previous information
And as the video showed
if you change any of the underlying information
the hash changes
So what does that give you
It basically secures the data
You know if somebody's tampered
So the only reason to really learn about hash functions is it's to say
oh
I get it
This is one of the ways to make this data tamper proof
So I have a question about a theo
theoretical event where a better hash function hash function is found
Then the
shout out
And how would that be implemented into the Bitcoin network practical
there needs to be a pretentious
And so
so
so how
how would any relevant change be adopted in the Bitcoin is always a challenge because it's a decentralized network
And all decentralized networks have a little bit of a governance challenge
The governance challenge is how do you do software updates
We all know that on our laptops are our iPhones
There's probably software updates going on here now
unbeknownst to me
right
They're probably just apples drop
And I mean
who knows what they're doing in here
right
And Uber
I really one of my favorites
Who knows what's happening inside this phone
But the commercial enterprise
the central authority
has a way to update the software
We probably sign some terms of use
That allows them to do that
And I in a decentralized network like this
there has to be consensus
And so the only way really to update the software for a new hash function
or for most everything else is
in essence
that the nodes
the operators of the software
collectively in a consensus form
adopted
So it's another way that not only is the data immutable because of these hash functions
but the software is
and that comes both with benefits and costs
Some people would say that's a bug of blockchain
Some people would say it's a feature You can come to your own judgment over the course of the semester
but the software is harder to update than software in centralized authorities because centralized authorities just say they just push the
Now sometimes you have to click and say update
So it
but
but don't be naive
Not every software
do you click
I mean there's some
that's just happening
But here you've got to have consensus
I know I didn't ask you a question about the hash function
but if it were a hash function that had to be updated and everybody said they had to quickly update it
There's
there's interesting debates about this
but you wouldn't need to go back over all 540000 previous
blocks
You could just hash all 540000 blocks
180 GB to 1 256 or maybe it's then a different kind and then you'd have that and would be tamperproof
So those are the key things
That's what we covered
really
what we're going to cover next
Tuesday's consensus protocol
We've talked a lot about proof of work here because everybody thinks of Bitcoin about proof of work
But we're going to talk about proof of work
the nodes and the native currency and the next Thursday
we're going to talk about transactions
Again
I try to break down this technology
If you want to forget about this lecture and you're going to go
oh my God
it was like going to the dentist
You could tell your friends that you actually know something about cryptography
It is called cryptocurrencies
So how can we not know something about cryptography
But it's basically those three things
It's cryptography
It's a consensus mechanism
And the so right cryptography
consensus mechanism
transactions
And we'll get through
And you'll see this matters to finance and whether it's got any use cases
So thank you