The following content is provided under a Creative Commons license
Your support will help MIT Open courseware continue to offer high quality educational resources for free
To make a donation or to view additional materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT Open Courseware at OC W Dot M
I T E D U
Welcome
welcome
If you have a desire to learn a little bit about blockchain and its intersection with the world of finance and money
And you're looking for 15 dot s 12
You are in the right place
If you're here to not do that and just hang out and have a good time
I guess you still hopefully are in the right place because we're going to have a good time this semester
My name is Gary Gensler
I'm a senior lecturer here at MIT Sloan
I'm also an advisor over at the MIT media lab
and I've spent a lifetime around the world of finance and money and public policy
And I bid at MIT this last eight months
And we're going to learn a lot together about blockchain and money
We're going to have a little bit of fun here and see what we're gonna do
So we're talking about blockchain money
That's where we are
By the way
I do cold call
I do call on you if you want to leave
Now
I understand
Because I want to have an interaction a little bit about it
So my first question for the class
for everyone
whether registered or not
how many of you have ever owned a cryptocurrency
Wait
wait
Let's see the odds
It seems like it's about 45% of you or so
All right
Excuse me
The line You want to keep your hand up long
You need to make
and how many of you have ever worked on any blockchain related projects in an entrepreneurial setting or corporate setting anywhere
Alright
good
So about a third in the room
Good
all right
So you all know probably more than I do
but I'm going to give it a shot
I'm going to always start every week with what are the study questions for the week
How many of you actually got the syllabus
This is not going to be greater to Simon
I just have to have a sense of who's who actually got this syllabus
So good many of
And how many of you actually did the two readings
It's not graded
I just got to gauge the class
Oh
thank you
Thank you
Write those grades down
by the way
no
All right
So the two main questions for this week's lecture really is what is blockchain and why might it be a catalyst
And I emphasize the word
might it be a catalyst for change in the world of finance
We could talk about a lot about things outside of the world of finance and blockchain may indeed have a lot of applications outside of finance
but I've chosen to try to just narrow the scope a bit
So this semester
really about blockchain and money or blockchain and finance
And secondly
you will see index cards on every one of these round tables
One assignment by the end of the class
you could do it now or later
I would like each of you to anonymously write on the court what you want to achieve this semester
It can be anything from this class
from learning about blockchain
from making money on Bitcoin from
I don't care if you tell me it's meeting your future spouse
I just like
what do you want to achieve in this class
I can't help you on the third
but I will try to help you on the things I can help you out
And Sabrina and Toledo will collect them later
And next Tuesday will tell you the results
What is it that you want to achieve in this class
And then we'll see at the end of the semester if we've done that
So that's just a way to help guide me
help you
So that's that's what we're trying to do
And so what were the two readings
One was a little thing I did
And one was a thing I did with some of my colleagues
And Tom
since I know you would you take out of the readings
that watching potential to improve the profitability or the the second one
Did you have a good summer
Yeah
did you raise your head
Did you own Bitcoin
No
Who in the class read the readings and took something different than Tom
He said there was potential in your first name
Alex
Well
I'm coming from the technical side
So from the technical side
all I see is a bunch of hype
And 10 years have passed since the launch of Bitcoin is very little show for it other than height
So I just got
okay
how many agreed with Elon
This isn't a vote or just two or three have any grid with Tom says more
And how many of you are too shy on the first day to put your hands up
So I'm going to start and go back the internet
How do I sort of I've come about this and sort of thought about
well
what is blockchain
What is it really about
Well
the internet started many decades ago before most of you were born
But 1974
I mean
there's some predecessors
even from the late sixty's
the Ethernet
which is really how two computers communicate
And then you had TCP IP
which is really the internet protocol of multiple computers
Compute talking to each other
And then later on in 1990
how do we move forward
Does anybody know what Http is
Where at MIT
Your first name would be helpful
Eric Eric is a is a probable for communicate the the web content web content type protects the transportation
right
You know who
Who's associated with the invention
And I don't remember right now
Anybody else
Anybody know who it's not In the readings running
Tim spurred league
Anybody know who's associated with TCP IP
It was a company initiated by MIT Acrylic
I think the bubble bag or something
I don't know if it was a company associated with MIT
but Vince Surf may have had some association with MIT
So these are the first three layers
And then there were companies commercialization
3Com and Cisco
And of course
Amazon is still around today
But there is something else going on
How do we commercialize the internet
Does anybody know what this scene is from
This is the first pizza sold by with Bitcoin
Good thought
First pizza sold by Bitcoin
But no
Is it from that movie hackers or something
Alright
movie hackers
I do from net the net
Do you know
Have you ever seen the movie
It's not a good movie
So this is the opening scene of the net
And yes
that's Sander Bullock
And the year is 1995
It's a cyber thriller
You know
a presidents involved
the defense departments involved and so forth
But actually
Pizza Hut is associated with the very first sale online sale anywhere in the world
They started something called Pizza nut
This was the screen
by the way
If you wanted to go on
you could order your pizza
And and but there was one problem
Does anybody know what the problem was with pizza Net
I mean
maybe there were multiple problems
No
a lot
I've caught on you
You couldn't pay
All right
You couldn't pay online
Nobody figured out how to move money online
You had to pay when you showed up with the pizza
So now I'm going to talk a little bit about cryptography
We're going to spend a lot of time on cryptography
It's is cryptocurrencies and and the like
What's your name
GG
GE
what's cryptography
Assume that the something crafty
cryptic
Alright
now you got it
You gotta start there
Anybody want to help GE out
Does anybody want to help GE out
Yeah
tell me your first aid
We're going to ask
We're going to figure out how to have everybody have name plates by next week
But we'll work with Ryan and do it that way
But idea
Yeah
it's the technology or the science behind encryption and decryption codification
So how do you encrypt a particular Texas that is not readable by someone else without having the decryption
Okay
so it's how do you encrypt something
So it's not detectable by others or in essence
its communications in the presence of adversaries
You have an adversary who wants the communication you want to communicate and not let your adversaries know that communications
And this is this is true for ancient times
So in ancient times
there was something called the cipher
And this was a way that you take a piece of leather or piece of cloth and have a lot of letters and both sides you'd encrypt and decrypt because they were measurements of the cylinder
Has anybody seen the the movie imitation games
Alright
the Enigma machine
Now the movie was wonderful because it said touring cracked it and he did help crack it in an automated way
But actually
the Polish government had cracked it in the S before they fell to the Germans
But and and touring built on all of that and and cracked it
And then in the 1970s
And this was here at MIT
To some extent
There is private key public key cryptography
which I'm not going to dive into today
But it's the heart of Bitcoin and blockchain
It's at the heart of the Internet
But it's about the key thing is communications in the presence of adversaries
How do you keep a secret when everybody wants in and get that information
And there's a long history
And MIT is at the center of a lot of that
A lot of early cryptography failed on the Internet in the early 90s and late 80s
David Chum and others tried to do things
And we're not going to debate these today
But you all have one reading
I think it's either next week which will give you that history
And it's worthwhile knowing about the history of failure
But cryptography is the reason why the Internet works today
Does anybody want to tell me what SSL and TL
TLS is
We have any computer scientists remind me your first name
Eric
That's
the protocol that Madam Sun top of the TCP IP stack to description using asymmetric case
which is public infrastructure cryptography
That's a cube socket layer is trying to lose it
So it basically uses asymmetric cryptography
which we're gonna talk about two lectures from now
But it secures the whole internet
So all of a sudden
you could deliver the pizza and get APS code
And I have to tell you
I never knew how this worked before I was at MIT
So PayPal came along in 1998
I mentioned this a whole bunch of other digital currencies then failed
But some of these people who will read later
like we'll read Nick Sabo piece on smart contracts later
Adam back
who created Hashcash
Some of these innovations were what Satoshi Nakamoto later used to
Some innovations which were really helpful and worked were Alipay and M Pesa
Does anybody know what MP says
I think it's used in Kenya as like mobile cellular enabled cash
right
In essence
they found out in Kenya
This was 1012 years ago that people were trading mobile minutes
They were unbanked
but they had cellular phones and they were trading their minutes as a form of currency and safari
Khan realized that and said we could help people be part of the digital economy
even if they are unbanked
And in Africa today
a half of the adult population
according to World Bank figures
is still unbacked
But half of that half has mobile phones
MP says 20 million customers in Kenya right now
So it's A
it's a form of money that's kind of swapping mobile minutes
But the riddle remained
How do you move money on the internet
Or in essence
how do you move value peer to peer without a centralized intermediary
And that's the
Of blockchain technology
So who solved the riddle and everybody to tell me who solve the riddle
Who solve this riddle now
Yeah
yeah
You're
you're wearing a tshirt that says Quentin Tarantino
So I think Quentin Tarantino should solve a riddle
What's that
What's your name
Ruth is
And who saw this riddle
So appear to peer cash
This is the actual dock top of an email that was sent out on Halloween
2008 by Satoshi Nakamoto
We don't actually know who Satoshi Nakamoto is
but it's a study question in a few lectures from now to ask you to tell me who you think Satoshi Nakamoto is
So I want to ask you that now
And he started with a very simple sentence in his email
I've been working on a new electronic cash system that fully peer-to-peer with no trusted third
It's kind of a modest statement
And so the question is
is this another internet layer
We're going to explore that this whole semester
I don't
I don't really have the answer
I don't think the best minds at MIT could really yet tell you there are some who are maximized and say
yes
it will be
And there are others who will say
no
And in this course
we're going to
we're going to review the minimalist and the Maximus
We're not
we're not going to try to center it in one place
But that's the key kind of question
So what is a block chain
We're going to do this in a lot of lectures
but I'm going to try to do it in in a short version
So it's time to stamp append logs
meaning you can add a little bit of information to this
And it's time stamped
So these are these blocks being added
Satoshi did not invent blockchain
This way earlier
does anybody want to guess what
what it was
You're going to have a reading about this later
But early 1990s
On the Stewart
What's that
Madores Stuart Hammer
Stewart Haber
Stewart Haber worked for Bell Labs
right
So one of your assignments
It's not gonna be a graded assignment
Just gonna be a fun assignment
Could any of you are going to say by next Thursday just could have some fun
Find the longest in time wise
longest running blockchain
It's not Bitcoin
And it's been running since the mid 90s
And your clue is The New York Times
And and we'll discuss it next Thursday
But this timestamped block block
block block of data creates a database
an auditable database
And we'll talk about ledgers
particularly next week
But we'll talk about ledgers all throughout this course and how it changes the world of finance
Now it's secured by cryptography because cryptography remembers communications and making sure adversaries can't pick you off
We're going to learn about hash functions and hatch functions that are a really important part of cryptography
And initially for databases and how to search and store information and databases
But in this circumstances
hash functions were the way to not only append the next block to the prior blocks
but really importantly to compress data to make it more manipulative and verify it
And as I've written here
tamper resistance and the integrity
digital signatures
which has to do the public key
Private key cryptography
There is no prerequisite this course
You do not have had to have taken computer science cryptography algorithms
If I could learn a little bit about hash functions and asymmetric cryptography
these are the two key important sides
And we
we have enough computer scientists in this room that can sort us out if I say the wrong thing
right
Maduras hopefully
And then consensus
So there's a really important part of blockchain is how do you decide who appends that next block
Because when I went back here
there's block of block each of these blocks
Somebody has to decide who appends
who gets to pick the
And that's what's called consensus protocol
And there's wide debates about consensus protocol
And we'll talk a lot about consensus protocol
But in essence
it addresses something
a term called the cost of trust
And we'll talk about Byzantine general's problems
which is another reading
The Byzantine generals problem was laid out as a sort of mathematical game theory issue
Some 30th years
That's what Satoshi Nakamoto Soft was
This last part that the Byzantine general's from
Pizza for bitcoins
A year and a half after Satoshi Nakamoto laid out blockchain Bitcoin
somebody sent an email and you'll get these slides
But this is the real live email
I'll pay you 10000 bitcoins for a couple of pizzas
I just want some pizzas
The guy who sent this
he says
I like onions
pepper
sausage
mushrooms
Lazlo
Now catch the date
This is May 18th
And he's offering 10000 bitcoins of 2010
But the key line is what I'm aiming for is getting food deliver in exchange for bitcoins
Nobody had used bitcoins as a medium of exchange
16 months into its existence
nobody had used it to buy something
And last low as a computer scientist in Florida was just kind of interested
And he put this ad on a on a an email list
Three days later
he still doesn't have his two pizzas
so nobody wants to buy me a pizza
Is the Bitcoin amount I'm offering too
Another day goes by
He gets his pizzas and he post pictures
So here's a picture of his child reaching for those Papa John pizzas
Anybody know what those 10000 bitcoins were worth back in back then
Chicago
I like the work now
Anybody want to say back that
What's that
$41
And Lasla was saying two pizzas are probably worth 25 to 30 because there's a whole email thread
He kept saying
why won't anybody get me my pizzas
You can make money on this today
Who are earlier
late yet last night
$66 billion
Yeah
So it's a kind of a cute story
May 22
Every year is called Pizza Day or Bitcoin Pizza Day or something
So what is blockchain technology
These are my words
But they're sort of picked from the literature and so forth
It verifiably moves data on a decentralized network and the economics of blockchain technology are are really around that verification in the economics of verification and the economics of networking
And in many ways
blockchain adds certain costs to the verification through this consensus protocol that will be studying
But it lowers some other costs of verification because you're not relying on a centralized authority
So it's really a trade off of cost of verification
I don't think it's
I'm not a purest
It says it's better or worse
but it's it's a tradeoff of cost of verification through decentralized networks
The data can be value
Like Bitcoin was a money system
Or the data can be actually computer code
And we'll learn a lot about smart contracts
And you could have the data being verified
computer code and algorithms and
My world finance
This directly goes to the plumbing of finance because finance is fundamentally about moving money and risk through a network
And that network is the 7 billion people that live in this world
It's moving money and risk
And you've all taken finance courses
or many of you have
And it's the intermediation of money and risks throughout our economy
But there's a whole host of challenges
And over the course of this semester
we'll talk about this challenges technical
commercial and public policy hurdles
Will they be solved
Will they not be soft
But it could be a catalyst
But we're not sure yet for change in the world of money and finance
So does anybody want to tell me the the role of money in society
And tell me your first name
Tomas Tomas
Basically
it's a way to
exchange things themselves between people
Alright
medium of exchange
Got that one without doing battery
I mean
exchange
This is a medium of exchange
So when you give me a second
yellow shirt
Yeah
medium of saving savings
All right
so that would be a store of value
Third
I'm sorry
the gentleman here
You need to account
You need to have account
Wow
alright
there we go
Here we go
So we're going to spend some time next Tuesday talking more about money and the role of money in the history of money
Which I think is sort of lays a foundational piece of this
What about the role of finance
I've already sort of said a few things about that
But and I'm
I'm sorry
I don't know your name
but I'm right here
woman
Yeah
role of finance
Sorry
I'm not going to tell any financial finance professor what your answer is
To raise money
So keep
keep going
I'm going to anybody else want it
Connect
connect savers and borrowers
Can you connect savers and bars
So connecting is sort of moving money
moving
make valuations
valuations
So that's the pieces of it sort of moving
making valuations
I use the words moving
allocating and pricing
Pricing is the valuations of money
But let's not forget
it's also about risk when you buy insurance
That's a transference of risk when you buy an equity stock
that's a transference of risk
If you enter into a complex credit to fault swap
it's a transference of risk
So finance is not just the movement of money
it's the movement of risk as well throughout the economy
And I always think finance
I always have thought this when I was at Goldman Sachs for 18 years
that finance sits at the neck of an hour glass
And it's why it collects so much economic rents from society
Because when you sit at the neck of an hour glass and billions
literally trillions of grains of sand go by
If you collect some of those grains as you get Uber wealth and that's those are for other classes
But finance can collect a lot of economic rents
The financial sector
though
has a bunch of challenges
We'll have one lecture later in the semester about some of those challenges
And we have a reading
I think Sheila Bear wrote something recently that I asked you all to read later in the semester
But we will talk about the financial crisis and some of the problems
But it's had a lot of crises
Fiat currencies have a lot of instabilities
Of course
we have centralized intermediaries
as I laid out
And we'll talk about collect a lot of economic rents
And so there's there's opportunity
Blockchain has real opportunity to kind of come under this world of finance and maybe do some things better
Central banking also have a bunch of legacy payment systems and those legacy payment systems are slowly adapting
but it's slow
And why did Alipay do so well in China is part of the story
Because there were so many unbanked
just like M Pesa in Kenya
But here in the us
we still pay two and a half to 3% for our interchange charges for Visa
MasterCard and and the like
And a lot of clearing and settlement still has a lot of counterparty risk
And one that I care deeply about financial inclusion
There's still 1
7 billion people in this world who are unbanked
And so we don't think of it as much in the developed countries
But it's certainly true in many products
even here in the US
And these are to be the opportunities
Finance is 7 1/2 percent of the US economy
That's $1
5 trillion of revenues
So any of you that are think about entrepreneurial opportunities
the payment system just here in the U S is a half a percent to 1% of our economy
That's 100 to $200 billion of revenues
I think Visa is about 18 billion just
you know
But you know
when you add up the whole payment system
that's 100 to $200 billion in payment revenues
So that's kind of the opportunity
Can blockchain technology come in
It's got problems
It's slow
It's it's performance issues still
But can it compete with that
Here are some of the problems the financial sector would say with blockchain
These are real live things that we're going to study later in the semester
They say it doesn't have the performance
scalability
a modern payment system
You need to be able to move about 100000 payments a second
a modern securities clearing
the Depository Trust Corporation
the Securities and Exchange Commission says you do about 30000 transactions a second
But we need you to scale and your computers and everything have to be resilient to a transactions
A second Bitcoin
you can do about 7 transactions
A second visa currently depends on the the second does anywhere from 20 to 70000 a second
you know
So it's just a sense of scalability and performance
We might get there
It might be 3 to 7 years away
optimistic
but there's still a bunch of performance and scalability issues
Privacy and security blockchains
by their nature or public
So they're not fully censorship resistant
but there's a lot of innovation about making them more private
But then that makes the public sector a little nervous
Interoperability
They don't necessarily work yet with other legacy systems or with each other
The Internet
one of the great innovations of the Internet
It became interoperable that that all of these different websites could kind of speak with each other
Governance is a very big issue we'll talk about
And one of the things about governance is it's hard to update the software of a block j
because if you create a decentralized where no one's in control
no one can collect economic rents
You also don't have sort of somebody with the ability to necessarily update the software
And we'll talk later about how Bitcoin updates its software and what Bitcoin core developers are and so forth
But FaceBook
you do know one thing
though
They're they're a company that collects a lot of profits and economic rents offer their 2 billion members
They know how to update their software
It's
it's a governance issue
That's a real life challenge
And that's why the financial sector says
I'm not sure this works
This is ready yet for me
And then thus
what are the commercial use cases and what are the public policy issues
So right now
the financial sector favors permission blockchains versus permission list
This is going to be about four weeks from now
We'll kind of go through these two differences
But I want to just frame this briefly
Permission
Blockchains have a known group of people who actually participate
The half of you that said you've owned Bitcoin
you know it to be something where anybody can update the ledger permission blockchains
You can't do that
In essence
you pick the three or 20
The Australian Stock Exchange is updating their clearing and settling
They announced they're doing a blockchain project
They're doing it with digital assets and they're using the Hyperledger blockchain
which is an IBM software open source software
But the Australian Stock Exchange is going to put it on three computers
which is called three nodes that they control
all three of them
The Depository Trust Corporation is looking at blockchain inspired solutions for some of their data warehouses
But they too are going to control the notes
I'm just giving it
That's permission
blockchains
There's nothing wrong with that
That's just how they are looking at this
Permissionless blockchains are like Bitcoin unknown participants
securities based on incentives
a cryptocurrency and crypto economics
Crypto finance is about 200 billion
But
you know
you have to update these slides daily
Two days ago
it was 230 billion
And this little pie chart is a little over half
Is Bitcoin
The next slice is something called Ethereum and then Ripple
And down the line
we're not going to spend a lot of time in this this semester
If you
if your goal is to how can you profit and trade day trade bitcoin and day trade ether
God bless
Good prosper
You could stay in the class
I just won't give you much advice on it
You know
this is not a crypto investing centered class
but I'm okay if that's what you're doing
Does anybody know what the worldwide capital market size is
Anybody want to guess
You know
this is 200 billion
What's it look like
I've already said it's modest
Hundreds of trillions
hundreds of trillions
Global equity about global bond and debt markets
250 trio
So it's still quite modest compared to that broad breadth of of capital formation and gold
If if bitcoins digital gold
what's the value of gold
All the goal that's ever been time
6 or 7 trillion
Yeah
7 trillion
yeah
So just give you a sense of scale
So there's also something that's interesting about this space is that it's outsize public attention
even as evidenced by the hundred of you in this room versus the size
It is real relative to the capital markets today
Yeah
there's a bunch of public policy issues
Will have a lecture
I'm a former regulator
I ran the commodity future trading commission
So
but this course is not about regulation
though
We have to always come back to regulation
We always have to infuse what we're doing with the regulation
But let me just give you a little framework
And then you have to be bored in a handful of weeks and read
I gave some congressional testimony on it
Yes
it will be required reading
Sorry
but it's guarding against illicit activity
A lot of Bitcoin and cryptocurrencies started out in the cyber punk sort of movement and libertarian movement
so forth
And it is true
You can use this for illicit activity
absolutely
But I would say crime is not new
Just the mechanisms and means are new
And so the criminals
yes
will use this and have used it for illicit activity
financial stability
Central bankers around the globe sort of
Will this shape finance
Well
it's only 200 billion
The financial markets are 300 trillion plus not yet is generally what they're saying
But for some countries
it's a way to get around capital controls
And so for those countries worried about capital controls
it's a very real and live set of issues
And then protecting the investing public
And when we do this in a few weeks
I'll go through each of these
the investor protection issues
And yes
the SEC
how we test and and and the like for those who wish to do their own initial coin offering
I'll give some
you know
broad sense of what the Sec is trying to accomplish
But it's a moving target
So this is a very interesting thing as opposed to many of your Sloan classes or your C cell classes or media lab classes
This is a very unsettled area of public policy
So it makes it and and and and if you all go off and form companies
you will actually be helping sort of set the the the edge of that public policy
At day 8
I would always say
just remember poet Riley
the duck test
This is a poet
Indiana poet
So those are from the US might not know the duck test
But basically if it quacks like a duck and it walks like a duck
it's a duck
So whenever you're thinking about public policy
folks like myself who once was a regulator
we think in the duck test
And then we secondarily think about the actual words in the Congressional Act
You know
where's the common sense
And if it quacks and walks like a duck
it's probably a security or it's probably this or that
The incumbents like this lioness in the corner are eyeing this space because there's a lot of volatility
And Wall Street makes money on volatility
Volatility is the friend of wall
It might not be the friend of investors
but it's a friend of Wall Street
And they also like the trading volumes and the spreads
Coinbase
the largest crypto exchange here in the USS 20 million accounts
They might not all be active
but that's the size of Fidelity's membership or account list
And twice D E Shaw and Robin Hood
How many of you have ever used
Robin Hood is a trading app
Wow
half of you
So you know
free trading
right
5 million members
For those who don't know
you can download Robin Hood and you can trade stocks for free
No commission if anybody's interested
Show up and I'll do office hours
Wonder how Robin Hood commercializes
They commercialize your order flow and they make money without charging your commissions
But it's a sort of wonderful app
Millennials love it
5 million members already
So you better believe DE Shaw and the incumbents are worried about things like that
The startups are also more willing to beg for forgiveness from regulators
They're willing to sort of take risks and beg for forgiveness
whereas incumbents tend to have to ask for permission
So there's an unlevel field that always
it's an asymmetric business set of risk about regulatory risk
Not always
I'm not like crying for JP Morgan
I mean
the big incumbents have also they have their and Coinbase is becoming an incumbent rather than just a
you know
Startup in a sense
And we'll talk during the semester about some of the incumbents
We're we're probably going to get Jeff Sp
Reckers here in mid November
He's going to talk to you about what Intercontinental exchange in the New York Stock Exchange is doing with Starbucks and Microsoft and the like
The financial sector use cases
I'm not going to go through these
but this is the second half of the course is going to go through each of these
And we'll do one to two sessions on each payment system
Central bank
digital currency
secondary market trading
the venture capital and initial coin offering space will do two course on that and move through
So what are we going to do in this whole course
Basically
our goal is to learn the fundamentals
That's about roughly the first half of the course
Pivot to two sessions on the economics
We're going to be talking about the economics throughout the whole course
But I want to
I want to really just focus
drill down on the economics on two of the discussions and then riff through the financial space for the second half
That's our journey together
To me
it's for anybody who wants to gain critical reasoning skills
This is not just kind of a
hey
this is going to change the world and revolutionize everything class
And so I basically think of an old Defense Department term called ground truths
It's when the general doesn't really know what's going on
but needs to figure it out and needs to talk to that
You know that that corporal on the ground
there's got dirt
you know
all over them and it's been shot up and says
Here's the real ground truth
We're going to try to talk about ground truth in this
in this
in this class and separate the mere assertion from the hype And some of your readings will be some real Bitcoin and blockchain minimalists from Noriel Rubini that uses words
I'm not supposed to repeat on a recording about this stuff to Paul Krugman
who and Joe Stiglitz and other Nobel laureates who say
no
It's not going to work or Warren Buffett to to Maximus
We're gonna try to cover both sides
Larry Lessig is honoring me because he's in the back of the class
who is an enormously esteemed professor from Harvard
I didn't know Larry was going to be here
And I did the slide before
But in 1909
I think you wrote this book
Larry
Is that right
Code and other laws of cyberspace
I put you on them
but I think it's worthwhile to think about Larry's 4 b here
And I don't know
Larry
if you want to say anything
but I'm going to try to infuse this course
And just how you think about this
the tech we're at MIT
the technology
And we're going to get you a lot of technology if you want more than I can give you is is a former finance sort of tight my whole life
There's going to be a bunch of computer science people in the class
we're going to hook and you up together with the folks from the media lab and sea sale and try to connect you to the technology side
If you want to swim deeper in that pond
But the technology really
really matters
And that's why we are going to go through hash functions and go through asymmetric cryptography and so forth
From a business perspective
markets matter
Why is it that incumbents or startups or are not doing this and that
Why is it 10 years in
And nobody's got an enterprisewide solution yet to payments that use block J
The law matters
The public policy
side manners
And the fourth of Larrys layout social norms
That's a little harder for me to teach
That's not what this class is about
But it also affects all this
It's not just the technology
the markets in the law
So it's not just a three legged stool
It's kind of a four legged stool
How do I do
Larry
I suppose
yeah
Alright
I really didn't know how he was going to be here
So
but I wanted to give you a framework for how your faculty member thinks and will be on this journey together
Range of perspectives
We're not going to be a Bitcoin minimalist or maximalist
I'm probably to be self-disclosed here a little bit
Center minimalist on bitcoin Smart contract minimalist max list
I'm probably pretty center
Larry is probably a little bit center max malice
I'm guessing
First off
I'm hoping I can be
but you're going to teach me whether I can do
Oh
so you're still
you're still center or center minimalist
What smart contracts and then blockchain
Maximalist or minimalist
I'd say a few weeks ago
I was kind of center maximum list
And I'm sort of skidding back to the middle
Permissioned blockchain
I'm a little bit more
And there is some in here alone is one of your Sloan cohort that you might know
Six months ago when we met was working on a permissionless system
And now you're working on a permission system
You have a stored up
Yeah
because like you
you bounce up into the market realities and we're going to talk a lot in this course about critical thinking about when do you really need the advantage of a decentralized peer to peer system where the costs of trust or such
But that's the right way to go
But I am 1 who thinks that there's also so much economic rents in the financial system
That's that $1
5 trillion of revenues or seven and a half percent of our economy or just 200 billion in the payment systems
for instance
that there may be times that you don't really need a decentralized system
But it just might be your opportunity to tuck in underneath all those economic rents and all those revenues
Now
incumbents will react
You poke an incumbent commercially Pokemon
I mean
and they're going to react
And that's why I think blockchain may well be a catalyst for change
even if incumbents then adopt a lot of that inside the requirements of the course
class participation is a hard thing to judge is a faculty member
When I have this many people
but I always think class participation matters
We
we made it 30% it which
if you have any advice on this next semester
30% to 2 individual write ups
one in the first half
which is up to
I think
lecture 10
which is basically the blockchain fundamentals
You pick a topic
I don't care which one
but it's you'll get
you'll get a much better grade if it's about critical reasoning
If it's really taking whatever those sets of writings are and and and not just repeating that which is in the readings
but really going the next step and saying here's what's going on
And this is a business score
You don't have to
you know
convinced me that you know something about computer science
It's like critical reasoning about the economic opportunities
the strengths
the weaknesses
the opportunities
the threats that old business schools are saying of swats
With regard to that weeks
whether it's about hash functions early on cryptography or you sort of wait during the foundational period to permission versus permission less you
But to please hand it in before that class is lecture
because I might during the lecture say
who wrote today
Do you want to tell us what you think
And it might help spur the class participation
And then a second right up in the second half when we're riffing through the use cases
again
critical reasoning
And then lastly
the usual approach of teams of up to 4
No
I don't want teams of five
I'll handle that right now
Three or 4 just and somewhere in the second half of this semester will talk about more of the content
And there's a couple of you in here that worked with me last semester in a smaller group
You know
I want you to do well
So I'm going to sort of give you a sense of like
what do we want to do
But it's basically the ideas
You're an entrepreneur or you're an incumbent
And what sort of use case are you going to pick
And and whether it's permissioned or permissionless sort of make a proposal
do a use case
Use your critical reasoning around this new technology
Somewhere in the broad world of finance
I mean
you know
and I'm glad to define finance really broad
yield pick
So that's that's kind of the piece act 1 or the fundamentals
I won't go through each of the pieces
but
you know
that's in the syllabus
Of course
Act 2 is the pivot of the economics
And act 3
our financial sector use cases
And hopefully throughout we'll we'll have a lot of fun
So the study questions for next Tuesday
Real quick
what are the roles and characteristics of money
So I really want to sort of dig behind money is but a social construct or social convention medium of exchange store of value unit of account
There's some readings about the debate
whether money first came from the barter system or a really good set of anthropologists and archaeologists and everything say no
It actually came as a ledger system and no one knows for sure
10 and 15000 years ago whether money came from the out of the barter system or more as a unit of account keeping account of credits and ledger
But I'd say when you read through some of those readings
you start to think
well
this is just a societal construct
And so we'll
we'll get behind that
What is fiat currency
Fiat currency
which is an invention really only of the last few hundred years
And we take for granted now
But how does that fit into that whole history
And importantly
had a ledgers
accounting ledgers
I know boring stuff
but it's probably why we came out of the dark ages
About 5 or 600 years ago with double entry bookkeeping
Sorry
I like ledgers
We'll talk a little bit about ledgers and how that fits into money and securities and so forth
And then layering in how Bitcoin fits on top of that history next Tuesday is not deeply about Bitcoin
It's just a little dollop on that
There will be 5 or six readings
One of them is a three minute video
The 3rd one
it's fun watch
It's just a funny little video on what money is
There's no need to read Knock Moto's full paper
When I said the email
I mean just the cover email
It's one paragraph
My goal
In the readings each week was not in each session was by and large try to keep less than 50 pages
You say you're going to look
Sometimes you go
it looks like it's more and maybe it is
I figure you're all going to figure out for yourself how to sort through the depth of your knowledge
But I will predict that some of you maybe as much as a quarter or a third of you are going to go down a rabbit hole one day and you're going to be doing blockchain for the next 48 hours
And you won't know where the time went because it is an addiction at some point that some of you will get because it's a curious notion
I'm not predicting that infirmity for all of you
I'm saying some of you will have that happen to you
So occasionally I have readings just like a lot of you
I think so
Let me just conclude and then take any other questions and write up their blockchain
I think
does provide a peer to peer alternative
I think that
I hope
Larry
I'll be able to convince it does provide and that peer to peer alternative addresses
cost of trust
It doesn't mean it's the only way to address cost of trust
But address is cost to trust
The financial sector does have challenges
Not just that
It has 7 1/2 percent of our economy in the US and similar ratios around the globe
But resilience
How it survives
shocks the financial crisis and things like that are are real and inclusion
7 billion people unbanked
But then if you look at other products
who has access to credit cards and mortgages in the like
And then fiat currencies can rogue off and others have written a lot about the instabilities that come that fiat currencies
And we'll talk about some of the history and why central banks exist and how they they came about it
Next key point is we already live in an electronic age
Satoshi Nakamoto and Bitcoin didn't create it
Electronic cash
electronic cash
I mean
Sandra Bullock couldn't pay electronically
That was 90 95
They did a sort of B rated movie about it
But by today
you pay your tuition online
Those of you who work get paid online
You pay your auto loans online
Most of our lives are electronic cash
not 100 percent
But in some countries like Sweden
it's getting very close to 100%
We'll learn together and discover that money is but a social and economic consensus
Blockchain technology along the crypto finance might be a catalyst for change
And then much masquerades as fact
But it's only mere assertion
We're going to try to sort through
you know
that those differences
That doesn't mean that all of you are going to walk out agreeing with Paul Krugman and Nobel laureate or or that this is just a a bunch of nonsense
The sum of you might by the but
but I think you'll come out with real critical thinking skills
And I hope that some of you will say
I figured out actually where there's a real opportunity in the world of finance to use blockchain technology and make it a better financial sector
democratizing finance or somehow providing a service at a lower cost
A better service throughout
I hope throughout that will learn together
And we'll have a A bit of fun along the way
So that's kind of my thoughts
questions
We have exactly what
18 minutes
There we go
But we can cut it short too
I don't care
There we go
Excuse you
Tell me your name
And we're gonna do placards
Ryan's going to work to figure out
you know
and do placards cause it's young here
I wonder how hard to form the final project
How are the teams formed
Traditionally
anybody at Sloan can can speak to this too
but students do it their own so that the faculty doesn't sort of try to insert themselves to help you
But we
we tend towards the latter half to say
well
who's formed up in in groups And when you know
if it's a smaller group
it's like
well
anybody is not yet formed in a team
Why don't you move to the left hand side in the room and just get together
But we could do that electronically
too
And you know
whether Toledo and Sabrina
who have
you know
good help and turn it
basically have a social network to help form the teams because this is a big group
You're right
But that's traditionally people
Students do it on their own
Other questions
Is anybody going to go out and sell their Bitcoin now or Okay
Larry
what
Why are you here
No
no
Let the payment
she said
No
but I
I'm here because I think we're gonna bring a critical skepticism to the whole field
And you're incredibly informed about the finance side
So I want to see the combination of those and whether at the end
I'm still convinced there is a there there
I I am convinced that there is a there there as we've spoken because I do think it periodically change the cost of trust around the world and that will benefit developing nations
But I think there's a lot of questions I still have in see how this conversation
Well
I thank you for coming in any week
You could be here any day
We benefit
And I hope it's really
this is meant to be a conversation
I'm not that far ahead of you
Simon Johnson approached me last October and said
what do you think about coming up to MIT
And Tom knows this story
And and and we were sitting down for lunch in DC
And it was a good time in my life
My 3 girls
I have three daughters
and I'm a single dad
And they were two were in grad school and one undergrad
It was a good time in my life
I said
why not
You know
come up here and get engaged in this digital currency initiative over at the media lab
And I've spent a life
I was 18 years ago in sacks on the investment banking side
helping people buy and sell companies called mergers and acquisitions
And then I went to the trading side
fixed income and went off to Asia and did a bunch of Iran
The fixed incoming currency and swap trading in Asia
And then my last job was the cofinance officer
So we were about a quarter of a trillion dollar balance sheet at that time
The gohman sacks
This is we were so private
which meant if we lost money
we were personally
I was a general partner was caput
That's a technical word
And but we had
we had 700 legal entities and 1000 people who could commit the capital of the firm
Those are people
We generally called traders
But
you know
as a fascinating period of time
I then went on to public service because Bob Rubin knew that I'd be a soft touch to service
He was the treasury secretary
I was a former partner at Goldman Sachs
And I went off to the US Treasury as assistant secretary and under sector in the late 90s
little different times than we have now for many reasons
But we were paying down the debt
We were dealing with the Asian debt crisis
long term capital management
that Russian debt crisis
It was sort of a fascinating period of time
I worked on a bill with John McCain
I didn't get to know Senator McCain that well
But it was just remarkable to work with
even for a short period of time called E signature
It was a bill that basically said you could sign everything electronically
And he was the chair of the Senate Commerce Committee at the time
It was wonderful
It's a little sometimes in government
you can work
work on small things
I worked on the redesign of the currency
And I could tell you stories about why it looks the way it does and how you can redesign paper currency
And for a future lecture
I'll tell you the one design feature that I is still in the currency and you can visually see it because and and when I asked for it
the fellow that ran the Bureau of Engraving said why
And I said
because it looks better
And I'm the guy that's approving it
And maybe could we get it done because we worked this out and it did look better
And he loved it
He was worried about the political risk of doing it
It was a better design
You just
I said I'll cover you politically
Let's do it
But then I worked with Paul Sarbanes
What became Sarbanes Oxley
I was a senior adviser
I worked and kicked around some political campaigns
We lost two of them
That would be the O 8 Hillary campaign and the 16 Hillary campaign
I was her chief financial officer
I was in OA to senior advisor doing economic policy and outreach and handholding
And oh gosh
and And then in the middle of those two campaigns
I read something called the Commodity Futures Trading Commission
which was postcrisis
What do we do with this is a real public policy shortcoming
And I looked at as an opportunity to
to
as I said
democratize finance a bit and lower risk
And so we tried to bring transparency to a 3 or $400 trillion market caught swaps
which are just contracts for transference of risk
And they are a form of derivative that that that we're unregulated
And we were trying to bring transparency to that and lower risk through central clearing
So that's sort of my professional life
And as I said
I got three daughters and they were well situated
So when Simon said
come on up
I said
great
And I love MIT
It's just terrific
terrific
And and you all are great
Unless there's other questions I'm going to let you go early
I don't
you know