The following content is provided under a Creative Commons license
Your support will help MIT Open courseware continue to offer high quality educational resources for free
To make a donation or to view additional materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT Open Courseware at OCW dot MIT e d U
Hello
everybody
Good weekend
Staying dry
I hope
Sort of a dive back into blockchain money
And we didn't
we didn't lose too many people when we did cryptographic hash functions and digital signatures last week
So I thank you for all being back
So what we're today's study questions again
What's the Byzantine general's problem
Anybody want to tell me what the Byzantine general problem is
Ben
So this is the general problem is
was a sort of general method puzzle
And basically what it is is how you coordinate
And they might be
So he's not acting in the best interest of the
I hadn't thought of that
Yeah
get it
So there
there
there might be how to coordinate when somebody's not acting in good faith is a malicious actor
But it also might be just somebody that doesn't get the communication
somebody that is
there's a fault whether it's malicious or not
How are we doing
Eileen
Yeah
how does proof of work and mining in Bitcoin address it
We're going to walk through this
I'm going to give you my sense of it
But does anybody want to give a short short version of prepared for
oh
brotish
The proposal book is essentially a solid stick
If you have a problem
stick with
or then I determine to speak with
by using
I want the CPU power to solve a problem
a certain complexity to prove that one consensus has been reached by a majority of the part of the business
Alright
so what brothers said is it's probabilistic
Instead of deterministic that you use CPU power
to form some consensus
I think that's what you said
I'm going to walk through this in more detail
But does anybody want to give a
another shot at it
I could say
One of is posted and my nurse
as I described to solving
I'm more forgetful
oh
I would also say it requires a lot of work
Suck me kind of pulling me cup
Okay
so easy
Take computers
So there is a fucking round
So
remind me your first name rehab
Rehab says it's about
people called miners or computers called miners
which we'll talk about today using computer power again
But transactions were part of of that as as well as to how it comes together
I'm not going to torture you
And I ask a bunch more
But Diane
one of the other important ideas is that even though solving the problem is really hard validating that the solution is corrected by
So what this ensures is that even though miners are taking a lot of computing power to solve once the person has been sold
it can be propagated to the most unvalidated
So
a key point that a giant
a giant raises is that once somebody solves the puzzle
it can be propagated across a network and then others on the network can validate it
So what
We'll talk about a little bit later is that it's a hard puzzle to solve
but an easy puzzle to verify
And this is an important asymmetry in essence
that there's a lot of resources to solve a puzzle
But once knowing the answer
there's very limited resources to verify that it's the right answer is
if it was not a symmetric
it would not work as well
So it's a key part of the design of many cryptographic things
but particularly Adam backs sort of novelty in the 1990s of a proof of work
I don't know if that's just a relaxed a bit for you or you have your hands up
Derek
That's just a relaxed pose
I like it
We're going to talk about other consensus protocols as well
Proof of work is not the only consensus protocol
but how to address ourselves to Byzantine fought tolerance and then some of the economic incentives
So we'll talk about the native currency
What's the native currency of the first blockchain application
Bitcoin
How many of you in this room owned a Bitcoin at some point in time
So you've all owned the native currency that helps a blockchain
You got the opportunity to read a paper that a group of us here at MIT coauthored
I hope some of you actually were able to download it
And then
yeah
go ahead
Ahh
apparently
even when you write something
it still goes behind a copyright wall
So I'm glad to know that it was actually
And then back to the National Institute of Standards and Technology Paper as well
This time
the next chapters and then a paper from about 25 years ago on the Byzantine
general's problem
it itself
So what are we going to do today
We're going to go back through the design
We're going to talk about consensus through proof of work
Bitcoin mining
It's important
it's relevant
but it's kind of some fun facts about that as well
The native currency
of course
Bitcoin of the first
But there's now at least 1600 different native currencies
What does it mean to have a network
And why do networks matter
particularly for blockchain
some of the other consensus protocols
and then just wrap up
So just going back to the review
And this is what we talked about a bit on Thursday
But I think it's relevant to just kind of bring it back
I found when I was first learning this
it's hard to keep all the moving parts Remember
There's how many so that graphic
You'll see all semester
But it's all the different blocks
And it's a pen only
What is a pen
Only mean
Andrew
what it was that matter
This word
A pen only that we talked about last Thursday
And so that's beautiful
right
So it's immutable now
of course
because cryptography maybe can be broken
But we use the word immutable that it cannot be changed
except for maybe as Elaine
So I like
that's in his book
You all have to see this
This is very clever
You know
a little in the standard of how to do a flag
Maybe it's immutable except for one out of 10 to the 40th times
It could be broken or something like can I interject and actually surveys
It's not that good
actually
So technically
Bitcoin and all of these permissions with their currencies
one way to attack them is to combine
get a lot of money and power in mind
But another way to attract them is just take control over the actual network
like the internet
So if you're an internet service provider or through China
you can actually cork Bitcoin with 0 mining power by just controlling the network
So it's actually
an assumption behind how this thing works
which is that the network works because everybody sees the messages that I agree with you
But there's also some assumptions
Let's say that China or any state actor chose to fork
one of these
if it's considerably less than a majority you can focus your heights if you control the network
If you control the worldwide network or just the network
the actual internet
I understand
So are you talking about the worldwide internet or are you talking about why countries in China
There's there's 50% of Chinese miners
I'm China
I forbid these Chinese miners to broadcast the blockchain
They find the block goes here
They find another block
It goes here it goes
Here it goes here
And the rest of the world will find the block goes here
And I have two forks goes here here
And I have two forks
we don't see
So we're gonna talk about forks a little later
Can we hold a lean's point until that
And then I'm going to share with you what Satoshi Nakamoto wrote about this very issue back in 2010
and he was writing to your back where you have mining power
He was assuming the network works out again
just to clarify it
Aleen's raising a point as to whether somebody captures part of the and if the internet itself by capturing part of the internet
you fork
The blockchain
And what I was just said
I would hold for later
but instead
I'll cover
Now is this question was raised in an email exchange with whomever Satoshi Nakamoto was back in around 2010 and his his answer to Lean's question
That I'm just helping share with you all
Is that as long as is that part of the internet that was walled off was less than a majority
And in fact
if it was China
because that was in the example even eight years ago
it would be considered with less than 50% of that within a reasonable amount of time
Maybe it would take a few hours
but within a reasonable amount of time
one chain would be
where the majority of the mining power was and that
that
that it could take a while
But the other one would would probably stop that
People would stop investing electricity and CPU time within China because they would realize some way
Now that was the theory
at least
And just get out on to that
Something to realize is like if you
I mean
you said we'll go into forks
but just people who don't know 1
anything after that
you go on hologram
So it's like if you lose connection to the main Bitcoin network
you still have that as long as you have your private keys
So if somebody in China realizes that they're on the wrong chain
it's not like you've lost your actual big one for they don't
That's correct
They don't want to lose it up to
And what if I can use the term prior to the four
Because a question
Brutish
so just to add to alliance point
essentially
So the way he says to be
in fact
yeah
so to add to Adam's point
actually
So
since the assumption underlying assumption for the president in general
problem in the context of a blockchain is you have the assumption that the network can actually verify that the what is being
to watch us over the network is actually a valid information
So that is kind of an underlying assumption If the network is contaminated
then the premise on which the problem is being solved or the or the protocol that is being
given here as a solution to the problem is actually not valid
if the network is
on time network
So that way it is indeed a so I think because I didn't pick up every word
You're just saying that there is an underlying assumption that the network protocol
the communication protocol of the internet is not compromised or walled off
but also that it's working
It creates a database we've talked about it through hash functions and digital signatures and then consensus
So what were the technical features
I thought about it a little bit from our last class to help just thinking through in three buckets
the cryptography and time stamping that we talked about last Thursday
What we're going to talk about today
the decentralized consensus protocols and the network of course
in the native currency
And then lastly
transaction script that we are going to talk about this coming Thursday
Now
it's not just three buckets because it's three lectures
but it's 3 buckets because they have something to do with each other
the cryptography
which is at the core of cryptocurrencies and blockchains
And it's just the core of a lot of things on the internet today
And the consensus mechanism
And then the transaction script itself
Cryptography is
as we've talked about communications in the presence of adversaries
also a form of ways to make commitments
And secure computation hash functions
If you recall what we talked about
what's the key
Of of a hash function here joke in to keep your touch on one
The elevator pitch
You just have to
you know
make sure that your sibling knows
What's it
Do you have to the private and the public key
right
That
that
that's a good
that's cryptography
but not a hash function
It's a fingerprint of a fixed length of any amount of data
I like that one way
Data compression
A crossword puzzle
Anybody here do the New York Times crossword puzzle in a mobile app
Good
So if you do a Wednesday's New York Times crossword puzzle
does it tell you whether you're correct on Wednesday or does it not tell you you're correct
When
when does it
I don't do the New York Times crossword puzzles
but I
Aaron
yeah
I'm actually
I usually do one in the past
but I think it will tell you maybe either that day or the next day
Or maybe
I mean
Stephanie
so it tells you as soon as you finish the puzzle
whether or not you have any errors
But it won't
But you can't actually check what the errors are unless you wanna like invalidate your streak for that day
So basically
you go to streak every time you go
I don't actually know if the New York Times use hash functions
but they could
they could because they could stick the whole entire crossword puzzle into a hash function
And it's a commitment scheme
And remember if you change even one thing in the input data
the hash will come out differently
So the New York Times could use a hash function so that Stephanie could find out
right
Because you can only push to see if it's correct when you finish the whole
And it either tells you have it or not
right
It's so I'm just
I'm bringing it to real life that a hash function
Just think of the New York Times crossword puzzle
And if you don't remember
ask Stephanie
we talked about a pen
only logs and recall that in blockchain and Bitcoin
there's a bunch of information
And the head of the block and that which is in the head of the block of
Is put together like the New York Times crossword puzzle
And we have a chain of blocks
Most of the data
though
is stored efficiently in something called a Merkel tray
Again
it uses a whole lot of hash functions
And so it's a way to be efficient
But it's also a way to secure the data
So now we're going to get back to your favorite thing
Digital signatures
So what's a digital signature deal
You group
That you are signing something like a transaction with your private key and the other person on the other side could prove that you were the one designed it with your publication
Perfect
so it guards against tampering and impersonation
I didn't go through this last Thursday
but think of digital signatures
Two different ways
A digital signature that you use without a hash and in Bitcoin and blockchain often
It's actually it's combined with a hash
And so as Joe Quinn just went through
you could have a private key that you sign something with the center's public key and a signature and exactly that
But it's also able to do it where you have a hash as well
You take all the data
all the message that you put it into into it with a signature
And
this is a little bit too complex
And it was last Thursday's lecture
But it's important to know that what blockchain is basically doing most blockchains do is they take a lot of information
a transaction
for instance
and hash that information
And why do we hash it again
Kelly
to protect it from other
Sort of like we have awesome Bob
how one has to be aware of each other's key and then verify the incoming
And it
it also compresses some of the data
But it's
it's a commitment scheme
It's like
this is it
This is actually the New York Times crossword puzzle that answers all the questions
So usually it first hashes it
meaning it's a commitment and then put a digital signature on it
And there was one last thing we talked about last week
What are Bitcoin addresses
Isabella
can you tell me what a Bitcoin address is
I guess
tell me where the Bitcoins can be sent
So it tells you where Bitcoin is being said
Ben
you want to help out a little
So it's the
Public key
public cashier
So it's closed
So it's basically that between Isabel and Ben
you've got it
It it
It's basically how any of the native currency Bitcoin can be identified
but it is a public key with a couple extra hashes and a little bit other fancy footwork to make it compressed and smaller
But it is literally what the
you can send bitcoins to
So it's determined by the public key
But it's not identical to
And I found a fancy little chart chart to define it
A private key leads to a public key
Through some form and in Bitcoin
it's called elliptic curve multiplication
But there are other forms of public and private keys
The public key
Then it gets hashed
And then it goes through a code that makes it shorter
which is the Bitcoin address part of the reason it was hashed
And part of the reason it goes through that extra code is to make it even more secure for
it's not the only reason it also compresses it a bit more
but those of you who have ever owned Bitcoin
you have a wallet and the wallet keeps those Bitcoin addresses
All right
so now let's talk about decentralized networks
The topic of today
Sil ver
Any questions about the review for last Thursday
I know it was quick a lot
I've always been about double hash part
Does that mean that it's now less invisible to be
And like the last immutable
Because if you take a 21st digit
cash and you contract it to a or digit
A few other options
I think that your
the question is
is this
if the output of a hash function is shorter
is it possibly can more breakable
I think mathematically that might be correct
However
this actually goes through two hashes
one
which is this mechanism called Shah 2 56 and the other one
I'm going to mispronounce
But down to 1 60
So I think because it's going through two different hashes
The answer is it's even harder to break both that
Any other questions about the review now
please
Derek
So he said
hashing the public key makes it more secure
I'm just wondering
cause like the public key is for the public
right
So like
what is the
where does the audit security come up
So the only thing that you're actually
showing is a Bitcoin address until later
And we'll talk a lot about this on Thursday when you actually do a transaction
you have to do
then disclose your public key
So initially
the storage is around Bitcoin addresses and some will advise
And it's why many wallets do this that you should never use the same public key twice
though numerous people do in blockchains
but to be most secure
you would constantly be creating new public key
Private key pairs are
And once you've used it
move on and get a new Philip Keys
Got it
So distributed networks
We talked about Byzantine generals problem
So I found some Byzantine generals and they want to all attack that cat
Castle
Or what if only three of them do
And two of them say retreat
that that's the visual
That's
that's the problem
The only way to win it in this mathematical game theory paper that was written some 25 years ago
as if they all said attack or all said retreat
But the same thing sort of came to computers
And the core thing about a permissionless system is there is no central authority
And if there is no central authority
had as a distributed network like the distributed set of generals come to some agreement
do we attack
Do we retreat
Well
it's based on a consensus protocol and a native currency
though
that's the key
Innovation of Satoshi Nakamoto is to pull it all together
But it was built on the backs of other people
Adam
back in 1997
he proposed a way to address email
spam
and other types of computer problems called denial service attacks
Now it ultimately wasn't used
I mean
he proposed it
It was used for a short while and then it wasn't subsequently used
but it's important to understand that the proof of work in the middle of Bitcoin was
created 11 or 12 years before the Bitcoin paper
And the key was basically require a bunch of computational work using hash functions
And so the email or the header of the email
this is Adam backs
not Bitcoin
but the email or the header of the email
went into the hash function creates a hash
But the difficulty of finding whether it's confirmed was
was it in a certain range of hashes
And he did that by the quote leading zeros
Does anybody want to guess why he did it this way Or or Orleans just going to tell us probably and not guess
But who hasn't spoken yet
Emily
you want to try it out
I'm not totally sure
Daniel
And move on just just like preserve some privacy around the emails
Well
so it definitely preserved privacy
But he was trying to put some computational work
Every email that would set be set would take one to 2 or three seconds of computational work that that was his in his original paper
It would take a few seconds
The fact
the fact that we earlier we were talking about the fact that we need a way in which we to make the puzzles
difficult to solve
but easy to validate
This is exactly how the whole thing is accomplished by
setting the hash into a fixed characteristic
like leading a number of giving zeros to what you get is to modify a small piece of all the information and try and try until you get that specific hash
And that makes it really computational intensive
But validating is just running one
And I have some
Here
Bill
I mean
it comes back to what we talked about last time with the nances
You need to try out a bunch of different random numbers in order to get the right number of leading zeros
And it could be
I don't know
I think it could be like leading anything
but he chose zero cuz it's nice
right
But like you need to try to like move around numbers in order to get the right number of
And in the email circumstance
his thought was it will take two or three seconds for anyone sending an email to do this proof of work
But it will take a nanosecond or less to confirm it it
But if you were sending spam and you had a computers who said millions of spam times two or three seconds apiece
that would be too much for the spammer
That that was it
So any one
any person sending one email
it won't be too bad
Anyone sending millions of emails
It would be lousy
And so that's why this concept was in the midst of emails
And it could be efficiently proved
So back to blockchain
the innovation was basically
how do we do this with a chain
How do we do this with a chain set of works
And remember Stuart Haber
that whole thing about the blockchain and the that
What's in the New York times this was
was that chain of information
But here
why don't we do a proof of work between the chain
And I found a little graphic
But
but the Shah 2 56
that's the formula which is is used to hash the header
the previous hash
the transaction hash
a time stamp
and a knots
Can you find a hash that has a certain number of leading zeros
This was the key innovation
in a sense
Or maybe Satoshi Nakamoto was just taking Adam Beck's email proof of work
Remember the reading for last week
A blocks this
this is colored green because each of them have hashes that
in this case have leading
If I'm right
is this it leading 4 zeros and leading four zeros
What if we change one thing
What's going to happen
Is it alpha
What
What happens if we change one thing
The hash will change completely
So what happened
What did we change here
I'll go back and forth
You change the pull up
What's that
Zad
You changed the point of use transaction
So that's hundred dollars
I guess in this example went to you instead of anger
Well
I why
why
Why should I be able to get 100 dollars for free
Well
in this example
I guess the Coinbase is for the miner
right
So there is one transaction dedicated for whoever validates the block gets right
Right now
5 Bitcoin
And so you add that in addition to all the other transactions that you're validating
But in this case
you're not actually this minor
So
you know
shouldn't be getting that much
So the little 18 minute video of it was assigned for last Thursday
I just went in and I was trying to
I was trying to get
I was trying to get the money for me
And it
it invalidated the rest of the chain
And that's really
that's the
that's the sort of innovation or genius is
is if you try to go into a former block
whether it's the last block or block 100000 blocks away and change one little whisker of information or one letter on that crossword puzzle
it's going to change the entire blockchain
And I bring it back to the crossword puzzles or a whisker on a cat
It's just any little bit of information about
So an innovation about hash functions became an innovation about timestamp and blocks
All of a sudden came with this proof of work innovation
So now to the chains themselves
The consensus of blockchains and many people would say that
in fact
the reality of blockchain is only the longest chain is the one that other miners
other people will build a pot
As I understand
though
it's not written into the base computational code
it's really just a consensus that comes about This is an example
the purple block and the black blocks are
the purple blocks are kind of stale blocks
They were mined
They were computationally solved
A proof of work
but nobody mined on top of them
And if somebody doesn't mind on top of them
then eventually
they're ignored some people call orphan blocks
But I'll call them stale blocks because they were actually created
but the information that's in them are is kind of worthless
It's not needed in the actual Bitcoin technology
This happens from time to time
but it hasn't happened in over a year
The technology
it's and you can look on various websites to find this out
Probably at the maximum
the longest stale chain
Get it out to two or three blocks
But it's very
very rare
So back to Lean's question
what if China carved off and had
The presumption
It may not work
but the presumption is
let's say China is the purple blocks because China's wat off its entire network is the presumption is there'll be some communication outside of the network
It might be on television
It might be by courier that the Chinese miners would know that they're not in the majority
and they would stop expending electricity to even mine in that circumstance is because whether it's a few hours or a few weeks or a few months
they know that their expenditures would be like
be worthless
Tom and these sale wax
These four blocks are the miners receiving Bitcoins
So in the purple blocks
there will be if I can go back to this
there will be a Coinbase transaction
But it will be worthless because it's a Coinbase transaction and a block that's not on the main block
And it won't be usable later
But in Bitcoin itself
there's software that says you cannot use a Coinbase
They output for 100 blocks
It's written right into the base code
And it has been since the beginning
So we do not verify
though
that
So in the situation where network is walled off
people start mining on top of this segmented block when they not realize that their Bitcoins are invalid for 100 years
Hey
say save for some external now
yes
Let me just go back to the
sorry
the chain
You're saying that the Tom's question is
is what if the purple side chain goes on for 100 blocks
What happens
And in fact
we have circumstances of that
Bitcoin has split between Bitcoin and Bitcoin cash
It was called a hard fork last year and for a moment
let's call the purple chain Bitcoin cache
It's not only gone on for hundred blocks
it's now gone on for tens of thousands of blocks
It is now its own native currency within that community
That purple blockchain is so long now that people have found value in that and it is its own native currency
And the reason I share that is to Tom's question of
well
what if China was walled off so long
It's plausible
unlikely
but plausible
that there would become some value and call it the Bitcoin China blockchain versus the Bitcoin global blockchain
It would be as what is money
but a social consensus
So who goes beside the award
I mean
as it fades into the amount for a top there
I think the other question that I
who decides it
So is it supporting the man music community
And what is the form of being
The question is of the reward
I'm going to hold a part of part of it for a little bit when we talk about native currency
but the reward is in nearly every blockchain is
is a new native currency of that blockchain
Bitcoin for Bitcoin
F or ETH for if the Ethereum
XRP
or for each blockchain
there's a native currency
Who the second question was
who decides it
It's generally
but not always hard programmed into the first release
Of that blockchain
Yeah
so back to a question on back to the question on a Bitcoin
a Bitcoin cash gift
The Bitcoin cash is the purple line
If you see
on the channel here
does that mean cause it's shorter compared to the block
Bitcoin chain
Does that make the under the
the assumption of the
the majority consensus
the value of
which is essentially the real
The question is
is
is if it's shorter
does it
So there's no
there was
there's no validity in that in that chain and they'll put it down
So
so there's
there's two
in using this chart just as an example
there's two ways
there was the main point of this chart was to say that the black
the black chain
as represented in black
is the main chain
And that is where the social consensus will stay
That's where the consensus is
And generally speaking
the stale blocks don't mean anything
And the stale blocks go away
And occasionally there is something called a hard fork where the social consensus continues to maintain
And I was using this chart as a rough answer to Tom's earlier question about Bitcoin cash
And if the purple chain kept going for thousands of blocks
And there was a social consensus to keep both chains going
you'd start to see separate
currencies
And as you have seen with Bitcoin cash
does that help
So I was
I was using a graphic to answer a separate question
I'm going to take two more questions and then go to native currencies
I haven't heard from Daniel yet
What a question is similar to the mining
So if your transaction is on one of the purple box
does that transaction boy
so is the it's not so much void
It's just
it's meaningless
It's
yes
in a sense
Effectively it's void
So I guess with somebody
if you initiated that transaction
would you be aware of it
And reinitiated
Very good question
The transactions
Will
still be in what's called the memory pool of anybody who's mining on the on the main chain
So transactions
which we'll talk a lot about on Thursday is coming lecture
Go in through the network
They're propagated through the network to the entire node network
And Bitcoin
There's about 10000 nodes
And they will receive those coins
And those two
those proposed transactions
So anything in the purple chain will still be in the other chains
Memory pool
1 more than I went in
You can make use of the hot name
Yes
yes
In the case of the heart post
So between Bitcoin and Bitcoin cash
what are the differences
And
whatever the differences in value between those two
That's a much longer question
And the question is
is what are the differences of value between Bitcoin and Bitcoin cash
And though
I think Bitcoin is trading around $6300 and Bitcoin cash is what
Thank you
Zan
That gives you the monetary
difference of about 15 to 1
But it would take more conversations about why that happened in background and so forth
So let me
let me
talk about the difficulty factor
So proof of work
at least in Bitcoins cays has a difficulty factor with regard to these leading zeros in the hash
And Satoshi Nakomoto said
let's change that every 10 minutes
Let's ensure that every block comes on average every 10 minutes
And to do that
define how many leading zeros there needs to be
And it had just about every two weeks
Every blockchain can be different
It doesn't have to adjust every two weeks
This is just what Bitcoin did
This is what Nakamura did to maintain an average of 10 minutes
So what
What has happened
Currently
It takes 18 leading zeros
And because this is in a 60
it's in a hexadecimal character system
Every decimal it is
What's that in 4 b
So it's 61st
maybe zeros and bits
And 18 in Exodus
Is it
So it's 2 to the 64th
The probability of finding a block is one over two to the -6
So what Eileen just said was that it's a very small chance of finding a block because this is the equivalent of 18 leading zeros
So it's more than 64
It's 18 times 4
Oh
that's
yeah
No
sorry
I can't do it with present with it
Ya
ya
his Phd in computer science
but can't do arithmetic
So this is the most recent block I grabbed off the blockchain this morning
And it has 18 leading zeros
And then all those other digits
that's block number 541974
18 leading zeros
the Genesis block
the very first block in January 2009 had 10
Leading zeros are
but the requirement that Satoshi Nakamoto actually put into the computer code was you only needed 8 leading zeroes
So the probabilities have gone way up
So let me take it off of a fancy
you know
numbers like that
And just say this is the actual Bitcoin mining difficulties on a logarithmic scale because if it weren't logarithmic
you couldn't really read it
And it
the difficulty was set at one
This is all scaled to
How difficult was it for the first year and a half of mining in 2009 in early 2010
And now it is at 1 trillion
It's actually more than 1 trillion because it's logarithmic
It's at about 7 trillion
It is currently 7 trillion times harder to find the answer to the puzzle than it was in 2009
And that's because there's a lot of computers trying to hash all of this stuff
Yeah
so is that where the collectors are
The pools of mining nodes work to be able to more efficient
correct
And the hash rate is now somewhere around
it's not Terra hash is i'm trying to remember what the
what's at 50 hexa hash per second
which is like 1000 trillion hashes because a Tara hashes a trillion hashes
Zan
I think it's worth noting
though
it it didn't scale linearly as like number of computers got on the network
It's also the hardware has gotten incredibly more sophisticated
So it's not that you can just assume there is
you know
15 trillion number of people that are mining Bitcoin
It's just the same people that are doing it better
I can't ask for a better setup than that
Bitcoin mining evolution did you
Did you see my slides
And you know
so what
What's the evolution
So it started with central processing units and Cpus
And I'm not sure my numbers are accurate because I might be using Cpu power today and not Cpu power in twenty O nine
Apologies for those who know CPU power better than mine
You could do about 2 to 20 million hashes a second on a CPU properly geared
apparently
I think
They didn't last that long by 2010
Some folks figured out there was something faster and it was called the
a graphics processing unit
We all use Gpus all day long because that's what gives us all our quick graphics
If you live stream something that on your laptop and graphics processing units
somebody figured out you can use that and you could hash faster
And then all of a sudden
hobbyists started to wire the Gpus together
And they could figure out a way to get between 20 million hashes to 300 million hashes
A second
I'm told that even today you could maybe get up closer to 1000 million hash is a second or a billion hash is a second
If you did a GPU rig
But that's yesteryear on Bitcoin
Now there's something called an application specific integrated circuit
an ASIC
Just think about a circuit that the only thing the circuit does is create hashes for
In fact
the circuit is wired
I use the word wired because I'm old enough to remember wires
but it's the circuit board is manufactured in a way that all it does is the Shah 2 56 hash function to bit quite mine
And the first A six
which are dedicated circuit boards
To do this
mining came out in 2013
and even since then
they have moved up the scale the most expensive that sells for about 3 or $4000 in Asac can do 16 terra hashes per second
or at least that's what it's rated for
If you go on Amazon and try to buy it and you could do that you
but you'd be competing with something like that looks like this
A modern mining factory for Bitcoin has thousands of Asics
They have water cooling systems to keep it cooled
and they're probably buying their electricity for less than 3 kW
3 cents per kilowatt
And they might even be paying off the local government officials and not even paying the electricity company and just bribing to get their electricity
Emily
double question
But in terms of like an economic opportunity cost using all this processing power just for mining Bitcoin
like is there a more efficient allocation of that processing capability in terms of like a more
a more stable economic usage
There are certainly tradeoffs here
And the aggregate electricity for all of Bitcoin mining
Now that it's 7 trillion times harder than it was in 2009
has been compared to the electricity use of countries like Ireland along the way to the electricity use of countries like Denmark
I think it's somewhere between Ireland and Denmark
See
Larry
a lot of that
The cost is make less assuming $10 or whatever he had currency and the reward is in Bitcoin volatility of Bitcoin makes it hard to answer that question because you don't know if there is an economy
value for you because you don't have a little bit more
So I said in our first class
I'm neither a blockchain maximist or blockchain minimalist
And you all will have a chance through this course to form your own views
But one of the debates is all right
The Emily's debate is this a good use of economic
A good use of resources
But I would note that all
strong currencies
strong monies for centuries have had something to limit the supply
And so now we're doing it electronically
And through this mining
it doesn't mean it's the best use
I'm just saying it's another way
So extracting gold out of the ground is very hard
And in the 19th century
to have big vault doors and security guards with rifles was a way to insure it
And one could even say that a having central banks takes cost
So I think of it as as a tradeoff of how you ensure a currency is a harder currency to create
But it doesn't mean that proof of work is the best way
which is
of course
then the setup to
the question of are there other ways to do consensus
So one other thing is all of this hashing
How is it distributed
And this I pulled off the internet this morning
You can see these statistics every day
Proof of work and mining has
formed mining pools
And these mining pools come together for simple economic reason that it's so unlikely to solve the riddle
Solve the puzzle of mining
And that if you can only solve it once a year
or maybe even once every 10 years
you weren't going to invest in mining
So mining pools started around 2010 to smooth out the revenue
So if Amanda doesn't want to get it once every 10 years
she might say
well
why doesn't all the 80 people in this room
You might
Amanda
I don't know
say why don't we all form a pool
And we'll are going to use our laptops
And now this is still 2009 or 2010 when you can mind Bitcoin on your laptop
But we could say
why don't we all do that together
And then all of us could say
well
Amanda
that's a bright idea
But could you create the Merkel route for us
Could you do some other things so that our computer doesn't have to do all that other fancy stuff
So then Amanda might say
well
I want to charge all of you a little bit
How about if I charge you 1% of the take and a man who would call herself a mining pool operator
That's what's happened is basically the economics of mining have clumped around mining pool operators and the standard fees range from 1 to 3% that the mining pool operator provides a number of services to the miners themselves
and those services are compensated
as I say
somewhere between 1 and 3% of the returns
But mostly it smooths out the economics for all the miners
It
It does some other things as well
But that's the primary
Sorry
I also had one question there because then you laid out the difficulty of mining has become increasingly difficult
and the cost of the electricity rate
the breakeven for the breakeven point has actually becoming a lower and lower in terms of electricity cost
So with that in mind
over the next couple of years
if that's the case
people will start to lose incentive and keep it doing the mining
And once that happened
once that happened to audio
well
it could go either way
As we said
just Bitcoin
this is Bitcoin adjusts the difficulty of mining every two weeks
So if there is fewer people mining
the difficulty will go down
And if you remember
I said you had to have 18 leading zeros
it might go back to 17 leading zeros or 16 leading zeros
And every two weeks it adjusts based upon the prior 2016 blocks
Did it average 10 minutes
If it averaged
for instance
14 minutes
then it will lower the difficulty if it averages 6 minutes
it will increase the difficulty
Kelly
is this for the steak comes in like
does BTC always get their 19% because they have the largest stake in the system
And so Kelly is asking whether this is where proof of steak comes in
What is proof of steak
Anybody who read the Coindesk article
see when you hide your first name
I can just call your US Air Force
That it's true
Bose Bo's name Cart says US Air Force
That's true
So proof of stake is the coins
All the coins are dispersed
And the verification allocation is allocate how to place it
So proof of stake is an alternative consensus mechanism
And Bo described it well
But Kelly
it's not related to this chart here
This is all proof of work
BTC has 19% of the hash rate that that means that they literally have about if the total hash power on Bitcoin is 60 Hexa
Do I have this word
Heck
substance exa hash
then 19% of that are about 12
I'm going to do
That's not the stake that they already correct
Most Bitcoin miners sell their coins
So the coins that are created the coins that are created each year are sold into the a broad
very few miners
Hold on to their coins for great lengths of time
I mean
they might for days they might
for
they might keep some for all sorts of reasons
And as I truly believe
but can't factually prove a number of of the biggest mining pools or miners are in places where they're doing illicit activity they're getting their electricity for less than what it's really costing on the grid
By bad act
actor
But nonetheless
they have a choice whether to sell their coins or keep their coins a question over here
And then I wanna keep going
If if the mining industry is like so formalized like you've got so many pools
what prevents all the pools from coming together and saying that
let's just like sort of lesser puzzle
So the difficulty becomes lower
And then the charge is much lower to each and everyone
So the question is
is
is what happens if the mining pools collude and come together either as a giant says to
let's say
well
why should we have a good so much mining capacity lets as a cartel like OPEC
the oil cartel say we should constrain supply and so forth
I think what constraints that is is it's an open system
right
But it's possible
It's plausible
I think the bigger question
And there's been a numerous echo
Numerous academic papers around this is what happens if the mining pools come together and try to do what's called a 51% attack and try to take over the blockchain
And that's a more interesting challenge
And we'll talk about that throughout the semester
And it hasn't happened as of yet
Let me
let me talk about the native currencies
Native currency helps
Do all of this
What's Nakamoto said is it was an incentive system
It was an incentive system
but it was also peer-to-peer way to create a new money and embedded in most blockchains
not 100% of them
There is something I put quotes around it
Monetary policy
in essence
that limits the supply of the currency
Not every blockchain has this
but the vast majority do
And when we start talking about ownership coin offerings
you'll find some that don't think
but Bitcoin limits it
And I'm just going to say what it is
It's created in a Coinbase transaction in each block
It was initially 50 bitcoins per block
But now now because it's halved every 210000 blocks
it's just 12
5 bitcoins
That's
that's the number of bitcoins you earn each time
If you mine a block that's approximately $75000 in value
Today
a giver taker 80000
roughly to mine a bloc
The inflation rate for Bitcoin right now is 41%
So think for any of you that have taken monetary policy courses or financial courses that talk about the federal reserve Bitcoin is growing about 4% a year right now
but it has every 210000 blocks
So the inflation rate will go down to 2%
And then later to about 1% and later about a half a percent
And it caps around the year 2040
And so whether Satoshi was one person or a team of people back in 2008
they put in place a monetary policy that is hardcoded into the computer base code
And it's supposedly gonna be there forever to cap Bitcoin at 21 million Bitcoin
I'm going to throw up ether just because it's an alternative currently that minds three F per block and the inflation rates about 7
5 percent in that's a different stage
a development
different inflation rate
But there's been a proposal recently to literally
it was a proposal by the programmers
We should really lower the inflation rate
And if it's accepted
it will be adopted in November
The fees the fees in Ethereum are largely paid in something called gas gas is just a small unit of Ethereum
what's the small unit of Bitcoin
Satoshi
So gas and Satoshi are very similar British
I think the limit of 21 million is wished at 29th
not 24
Wait
did it's not 2040
21 point
Oh
yes
Wait
you think it's 21 40 closing out
What's that
All right
So I typed poorly
Aviva
did you have question
I
this means Bitcoin is a deflationary currency
Well
Eileen says it's Bitcoin and deflationary currency
depending upon
your use of that word
But others have written that Bitcoin is a deflationary currency because it's not growing
If the economy is growing at explicit and x percent is bigger than how Bitcoin is growing
that would
that would sort of define it as deflationary
I would just note that those who are fond and there's a lot of academic literature
And this goes back decades
if not centuries
for hard currencies
where monetary policy is absolutely formula driven
whether it's the Taylor rule or other rules
rulebased monetary policy would have a fondness for what you could maybe put in computer code
Those who think that humans should be involved
And many people think there is a need for some human involvement would say this is too hard coded
and you'd want something where you could modify and change it
and it would be dangerous
in times of war and times of stress and times of economic peril or like the 2008 crisis that this would make a crisis worse
And so the academic literature and the real life reality in the last couple of hundred years of hard currencies hard monetary policies versus human involvement and some judgment is kind of an an interesting debate that goes right in the middle of all of this
what we consider it is a reincarnation of art is an aspect
It's a class of asset that has some aspects of the cars
So the question is
is this is a real currency
Or is it just a asset that has aspects of of the currency
Ben
what do you think
So there were the three rolls and or three places you could define a currency
It was the unit of account store value
medium of exchange
So I guess this has all of those attributes you could call it accounts
You're saying if it has all of those
it does that
All right
DOS
alright
so Ben thinks yes
How many people were within
As of September 18th
not 21
So Isabelle is there Zen
So how many people think
Tom
How many people think
Not right
I don't
I think that you all get to decide yourself
Mark Carney
who is the governor of the Bank of England
gave a speech earlier in the year
which is assigned at a later class
And he says
I don't think we should call him cryptocurrency
So they should be called crypto assets
They're not yet evidencing all three of these things
So that's Mark Carney
who I have great respect for
But there are others that say
no
it's evidencing enough
I would say this
though
It's plausible that they will they and this
this
if you take nothing else from the class
it's plausible in my view that they could not provide
you could have digital currency that does not have a central authority
I mean
I think that innovation is there
whether you call it a cryptocurrency or cryptoasset at this point in time
I leave to all of you
there won't be a right answer to that on any paper
You submit you can use whichever term
You think fits your thinking
I want to talk about the network
We only have 10 minutes
but the network is important
And a lot of times when you talk about Bitcoin and blockchain
folks aren't going to talk about it
But I want to quickly hit 8 or 9 players on the network
There are full nodes
A full node is
is a group is a computer
I should say that stores the full blockchain technology
and is able to validate all transactions
It doesn't have to
It's a volunteer thing
but it can validate all transactions are a pruning node
You're not going to read a lot about it
But I just have it
It prunes transactions once they've validated and they have a certain age
You're saying
you know
all of those early transactions were not going to focus
There's been
Probably six times the number of transactions that have happened compared to the actual extent transactions right now
So all the transactions that have ever happened
6 of them have already been used
They're not around anymore
Why do we have to lug it around in our dataset
So you could have a pruning node
lightweight nodes
which if any of you have a Bitcoin wallet or any other wallet
you probably have a lightweight
some form of lightweight node or what's called an SPV node
It stores just those blockchain headers rather than all this detail underneath a lot less storage
But a lightweight node has to rely on the full nodes for verification because the lightweight node is not going to be doing that
And so on
Miners
we talked about miners
I want to just mention miners don't have to be full nodes
Amanda
you're running this mining operation for the whole class
and we're paying you 1 to 3%
But you're so you're Sloan
right
You're probably charging at the high end
So do you think that Amanda
as a mining pool operators operating a full node
Hi
Tom
Yes
saying it tentatively
But Tom
you're paying a man to 2% of your fees
Don't you want to make sure she's validating everything
Yeah
what's that
She just thinks
oh
she thinks three per cent
But
but any of you who are just miners
remember
Amanda is our pool operator
anybody's Andrew
do you think you need a full note
If if Amanda is no
so a lot of miners are not operating full nodes
they've got all those racks of Asics
They're running all their electricity and they are paying a man at a check on it
Don't let them down a link
I think this is a terrible thing because in principle
you have like 2030 mining codes
which means you have 2030 computers
which validate the neural deposit block and sort of the thing that everybody wants to believe is that these systems are decentralized and you have thousands
So I might start calling you Norio Rabbini
but I won't
But Norio Rabbini
who is an economist
he sometimes called Dr Doom
and he likes that phrase because he caused downturns in the market
There's
there's a later reading and I might have even done a video of Rabbi has this video that it's not decentralized in mining pools or at Achilles heel of the system
but the full nodes
the 10000 nodes actually still do validation
And there's an interesting social construct where there's a lot of nodes doing in innocence
noncompensated work
validating transactions beyond Amanda and any minor Andrew could could validate if he wants to
So there's a lot of free riding that goes along and the economics of free riding
And then there's wallets
which probably 30 or 40 of you have when your computer somewhere
they store and view and send all the transactions
But importantly
also create the key pairs
So a lot to cover
There's one that's not a node itself at all
It's called the mempool or the memory pool
And we're going to talk about this more on Thursday
But the memory poll stores all the unconfirmed and but yet already validated
So they've been validated by somebody
A transaction goes out into the network
A full node validates it is
and it's put in a memory pool
And Amanda grabs the memory pool and sends it out to everybody in this class in a block
And then we mine it
We're not going to chat much about these right now
But we talked about there was a Coindesk article
How many of you actually skimmed
It looked at it
And did it mean anything to you or just meant that there's some alternative
What's that
Priya
Is that there's some alternative
That's what it meant to me
The first time I looked into this about 6 months ago
But I want to just mention what the alternatives come down to
They generally randomized or delegate the selection
So rather than rather than saying any one of 10000 nodes can prove that this works and it
they use various mathematical means randomized or delegated
And sometimes they do a little bit of delegation and randomization to pick who's going to validate the next block
It all comes down to who is picking the next block
Is it by Adam Beck's sort of as Satoshi Nakamoto
Put out there
We'll call it Nakamoto consensus proof of work
And you'll you'll have a paper for Thursday that talks about Nakamoto consensus
the Clark paper
But or is there some other randomized delegated way to do it
In some of them
they have a second check
If there's a delegated person to validate something
They put a second check in there that there is another group that that officiates and says whether it's correct
And so there's proof of stake
which is based on the stake you have in the underlying currency
There's proof of activity
which is kind of a high bread of proof of work and proof of stake
Proof of burn
Are you willing to give up coins
A proof of capacity
Do you have storage capacity
And you might have a tiered system
And the major
permissionless blockchains all use proof of work
And the reason is nobody's really solved all of these other alternatives
No one's really solved for a couple of problems in them
But they usually find a way to be more efficient through delegation and randomization and might have a backup set of checks on it
Dash and Neo will say that they use proof of steak
but they're actually kind of using some form of of master nodes or or or set up professional nodes
But Dash and Neo are kind of
I think the 13th and 15th largest market value cryptos
which means everything else kind of and ripple
doesn't
It
Ripples really almost like a permission system rather than permissionless
I mean
they would say they're permissionless
but it's a confirm firm set of nodes that in the node system
So that's it for today
We're going to do transactions
On Thursday
I moved that study question
And then I'm going to ask you to read through the Clark paper
which is really the academic pedigree
Where is this built on
What's the background
But I think it's a good way to bring it all together
And remember
on Thursday
you all come in to answer this question
your own view as to who Satoshi Nakamoto is
There is no right answer
But of MIT S blockchain money class can answer that
I'm sure that we'll get a right up somewhere about it